Great, so today's דף daf is קי"ג. Kuf Yud Gimmel. We start
in the middle of קי"ב עמוד ב'. Kuf Yud Bais amud Bais.
The גמרא Gemara had been dealing with issues about when you can
because there was a whole question about somebody who died and left
a גזילה gezeila over in front of his children. And are they
גדולים gedolim or קטנים katanim and can you have a judgment against
קטנים katanim because it's as if the בעל דין baal din isn't
present? Then the גמרא Gemara had a whole discussion about מקבלין עדות
שלא בפני בעל דין, mekabelin eidus shelo bifnei baal din, and under
what circumstances can you, and a sort of set of collection of
circumstances about if the person either there's an urgency, the witnesses are
leaving, or they're ill, or whatever, and you've called the person and
he refuses to show up to court. So there's a very important
question that תוספות Tosafos has about whether those are, you need both
of those conditions or only one of them. Let's say somebody is
being, you know, summoned to court and he refuses to show up,
but you don't have that other urgency. So the גמרא Gemara sort
of sounds at certain places that that's enough to go ahead with
the case, but at other places it sounds like you need that
combined with an urgency. But anyway, so you went, you're going ahead
with the case, and then the גמרא Gemara also has a question
about: can you do קיום השטר? kiyum hashtar? Since the שטר shtar
is already signed, maybe it's not like a קבלת עדות kabalas eidus
accepting testimony not in the person's presence because the need to sort
of verify, validate the signatures is only rabbinic, so maybe you can
go ahead even without the, you know, without the person being present.
So that was questions about מקבלין עדות שלא בפני בעל דין. mekabelin
eidus shelo bifnei baal din. Okay, but now we're going to pick
up with...
let's take a look.
Okay,
so let's sort of take a look with אמר רבא amar Rava
I mean we'll go back a little bit, but just to get
the gist of it four lines before the lines get wide. אמר
רבא הלכתא מקיימין ליה לשטרא שלא בפני בעל דין. Amar Rava, hilchasa
mekayemin lei lishitara shelo bifnei baal din. So even if the guy
isn't around, we can do קיום השטר. kiyum hashtar. ואפילו עומד וצווח,
ve'afilu omed vetzoveach, and even if the guy is saying it's a
forgery, okay, which is, you know, unless you bring some evidence to
that fact, we would be
מקיים השטר. mekayem hashtar. ואמר נקטו לי זימנא עד דמייתינא סהדי ומרענא
ליה לשטרא ve'amar nakitu li zimna ad demaysina sahadai marenaleh lishitara if
he says wait, I need some time, I'll bring witnesses to prove
that the שטר's shtar a forgery נקטינן ליה. nakitinan leh.
So then we give him some time. אי אתא אתא ei asa
asa if he's able to produce a witnesses good, or if he
comes, shows up to court, he comes. ואי
לא אתא נטרינן ליה ב' ה' ב' veei lo asa, natrinan leh
beis hei beis we wait ב' ה' ב' Be-Ha-Be because the court
meets on Mondays and Thursdays, so Monday, Thursday, and a Monday. אי
לא אתא, ei lo asa, and if at that state he hasn't
shown up, then we, even though he's claiming it's a forgery, we
proceed with the case. וכתבינא פתיחא עילויה, vechasvina pesicha ilaveih, so and
we write a like a judgment against him essentially. רש"י Rashi says
that it's a שמתא, shamta, put him in חרם cherem because he's
not paying up his debt.
תשעים יומין tishin yomin for
90 days.
תלתין קמאי לא נחתינן לנכסיה tlasin kamayei lo nachtinan lenichseih the first
30 days we don't actually go and seize his property. So now
there's more generic about somebody who has a judgment against him and
what, when do we wait for him to actually pay up and
at what stage do we go ahead and take action. So we
give him 90 days. For the first 30 days we don't seize
his property, דאמר קטרח בזוזי, de'amar katarach bezuzai, and he's, if he's
trying to borrow the money, we'd rather he be able to, you
know, we not have to seize his, you know, his car and
his house and whatever, so we want to give him an opportunity
to borrow the money. מציעאי, metziyei, the middle 30 days, נמי לא
נחתינן לנכסיה, nami lo nachtinan lenichseih, we also don't seize the property
even though we gave him time to borrow the money, דאמר דילמא
לא אשכח למיזף וקטרח לזבון, de'amar dilya lo ashcach lemiyzif vekatarach lezabin,
because maybe okay he can't borrow money but we want to let
him, give him the opportunity to sell his property and he can,
you know, make a get a better deal than if we were
to seize the property. So we want to give him, you know,
that, you know, that accommodation. בתראי, basrayei, the last 30 days, נמי
לא נחתינן לנכסיה, nami lo nachtinan lenichseih, we also don't. Why? He,
we gave him time to sell his property, דאמר לוקח גופיה קטרח
בזוזי. de'amar loke'ach gufei katarach bezuzai. Yeah, maybe he's got a potential
buyer, now the buyer has to get the money, has to borrow
the money in order to buy the property. So we give him
this time in order so that even, so that he can get
like the best deal out of it, you know, out of, he
doesn't have to lose the maximum amount. But if after that amount
of time לא אתא, lo asa, he doesn't come, כתבינא אדרכתא אנכסי,
chasvina adrachta anichsei, then we write a judgment against his property to
seize his property and we're just going to seize it and, you
know, collect it. והני מילי דאמר מייתינא. vehani mili de'amar maysina. That's
all if he says that okay I'm trying to collect the money,
then we give him these 90 days. אבל אמר לא מייתינא, aval
amar lo maysina, he says, "I reject your whole judgment," then לאלתר
כתבינן, le'altar chasvinan, and then we don't give him any allowance and
then we just seize the property right away.
I'm going to come, meaning I'm going to...
he's before the ב' ה' ב' Be-Ha-Be process, it's like if if
he says I'm going to participate in the case, right? I'm going
to come.
Right, you mean we're going back to the guy who's refusing to
show up, who's saying he's going to come to court? I don't
think so because if you take a look all the words of
אתא asa here, I don't think we're anymore in the case of
שלא בפני בעל דין, shelo bifnei baal din, right? מייתינא... maysina... סהדי,
sahadi, אי עשה עשה לא עשה לא עשה כתבינן על תשעים יומין,
i asa asa lo asa lo asa kasvina al tishim yomin, right?
So you’re reading the לא עשה lo asa meaning that he’s just
like refusing to come to court, but it doesn’t sound that way,
it sounds like he’s... maybe, I mean I hear it, you’re right.
I mean maybe it means like he’s claiming that he’s trying to
produce witnesses. Yeah,
it’s...
but the 90 days is not, it’s after we’ve decided he’s not
producing witnesses, we’re giving him... so you mean that if he says
he’s not going to come we don’t wait the בה"ב. Bahab. Oh,
okay, so we’re not in the 90 days. Oh, that could be.
Okay, you’re right, because the עשה asa phrase before was about waiting
the בה"ב. Bahab. Okay, I accept that. Okay, והני מילי, v’hani mili,
so that idea that you wait the בה"ב Bahab when we’re trying
to מקיים m'kayem the שטר shtar דאמר אתינא, d’amar atina, because he
says give me time that I want to come and I want
to produce witnesses. Okay, I think that’s correct. אבל אמר לא אתינא,
aval amar lo atina, if he sort of rejects the whole proceedings,
then לאלתר כתבינן, l’altar kasvina, then we would go ahead and issue
a judgment against him right away. Right, we might still give him
the 90 days, but we don’t wait the בה"ב Bahab before issuing
the judgment against him. Yes, I think that’s correct. Okay, והני מילי
במלווה, v’hani mili b’milva, now all of that is when there’s a
judgment against him. אבל בפיקדון לאלתר כתבינן, aval b’pikadon l’altar kasvina, I
see what your question was because you’re reading it still in the
context of here about the person who’s refusing to show up. So
is there a שטר shtar on a פיקדון? pikadon?
Yeah, I read it differently. I read it that it’s... that this
case is... is that... is that
if it’s a loan, then he has to collect the money, but
if it’s a... you know, and maybe he has to produce the
money, but if it’s a פיקדון, pikadon, then, well, and he’s not
producing the פיקדון, pikadon, then it’s not like he had a right
to spend the money so we don’t give him as much allowance
to collect the money.
Exactly. Yeah, exactly.
So
but right... וכי כתבינן אמקרקעי אבל אמטלטלי לא. v’chi kasvina a-karka aval
metaltlei lo. Right because here the כתבינן kasvina is clearly, it’s clearly,
you’re right, it’s ambiguous. Is the כתבינן kasvina the שמתא shamta or
is the כתבינן kasvina the actual collecting? It seems to me here
when we’re moving to the מלווה milva and the פיקדון, pikadon, we’re
definitely at the stage here of the collecting. Like we give you
time to put together the money for a loan because you had
a right to spend the money. But for a פיקדון pikadon we
don’t give you time and we seize property right away. And then
it starts saying, and what type of things do we seize? We’re
going to seize מקרקעי, karka, but for מטלטלין metaltelin we’re not. Why
are we not going to seize מטלטלין? metaltelin? I mean, we’d think
the easier thing to do is to seize מטלטלין metaltelin in payment
of the debt because
דילמא dilma what’s going to happen? This guy is still claiming that
he can go ahead and prove that the שטר shtar was a
forgery. So, and we’re going to go ahead and we’re going to
take his property, his מטלטלין. metaltelin. Now, דילמא שמיט ואכיל להו מלווה
למטלטלי, dilma shamit v’achal lehu mialve l’metalteli, so the... so the... the
creditor’s now going to go ahead and we’ve... he’s going to consume
this property that we’ve now seized on his behalf because it’s מטלטלין,
metaltelin, he’ll take it somewhere, he’ll take your car, he’ll sell it,
whatever he’ll do with it. וכי אתי לוה ומייתי סהדי ומרע ליה
לשטרא, v’chi atei loveh u’meiti sahadi u'marea lei lishtar, and then when
the לוה loveh ultimately is able to produce the witnesses that he
claims that he has, לא משכח מידי למיגבא, lo mishkach midi l’migba,
then he’s not going to be able to get his money back
from the מלווה. malve. So we want any collection in the particular
circumstances, it doesn’t seem like in all cases. This is in cases
where the guy is claiming he has witnesses and has yet to
be able to produce it, which is very interesting. So that allows...
so therefore we’re going to have a little bit of a, you
know, of a pay attention to that, have a little bit of
a we want to be able to reverse it if necessary, because
just because he hasn’t produced it now doesn’t mean he won’t produce
it. So therefore when we seize the property, we want it to
be able to be that if we have to we could able
retrieve it. And therefore we don’t want to seize property that is
a... that’s... that’s... that’s מטלטלין metaltelin because then the לוה loveh won’t
be able to retrieve it. Now, וכי אתי לוה... v’chi atei loveh...
so therefore, ואית ליה מקרקעי למלווה, v’islei m’karka l’mialve, but if the
מלווה mialve actually has מקרקעי karka himself, כתבינן. kasvina. Then we allow...
then we seize chattel, we seize מטלטלין metaltelin because then even if
the guy took the car and sold it and then he doesn’t
have the money etc., the לוה loveh can always now get his
money back from the מלווה's malve מקרקעי. karka. So as long as
somebody has מקרקעי, karka, you know, it could always be reversed. Either
you’re seizing the מקרקעי karka and then you give him back the
מקרקעי, karka, or you’re seizing מטלטלין metaltelin and you could give him
the מלווה's malve מקרקעי. karka. So that’s what the גמרא Gemara initially
says. ולא היא. v’lo hi. But it’s not true. אדרכתא אמטלטלי לא
כתבינן, adrakhta a'metalteli lo kasvina, we do not write a... אדרכתא adrakhta
which is again like a document to seize the property on מטלטלי,
metalteli, why? אף על גב דאית ליה מקרקעי חיישינן שמא תכסיף. af
al gav d'islei m'karka chashinan shema techsif. We’re afraid that the מקרקעי
karka of the מלווה malve would go down in value. And of
course,
I mean, you know, what do you mean? Let’s say the מלווה's
malve millions of dollars worth of מקרקעי karka and it’s a thousand
dollar, you know, thing, judgment. So it doesn’t seem like it sort
of explains all cases. But the point is if the לוה loveh
is claiming that the שטר shtar is a forgery, even if he
hasn’t produced the witnesses, we always want to allow an easy reversal
of the judgment. So we always want to have him just seize
the מקרקעי karka so we could give the same מקרקעי karka back.
Okay, that’s... that’s interesting that that claim is enough for us for
us to leave that open door. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara goes on, וכי כתבינן אדרכתא, v’chi kasvina adrakhta,
and when do we write this אדרכתא, adrakhta, this property... this document
to seize property? property. And when we write it, מודעינן ליה, moda'inan
leh, we inform him. Okay, that you should be aware that we
have now written a document against you that you know to come
and seize your property. והני מילי Vehani milei דמיקרב, demikrav, that's only
if he's nearby. אבל מרחק לא, Aval merchak lo, but if he's
far away, we don't, you know, we don't sort of wait to
write it until we can like inform him about it. ואי
מרחק ואיכא קרובים, Ve'im merchak ve'ika krovim, but if however there are
he has relatives around, אינמי ואיכא שיירתא דאזלא ואתיא התם inamei ve'ika
shayrasa de'azla ve'asya hasam or there are caravans that travel to where
this guy lives, then משהינן ליה תרי עסר ירחי שתא עד דאזלא
ואתיא שיירתא. mashinan leh srei asar yarchei shata ad de'azla ve'asya shayrasa.
So then we give time for the, you know, a year, this
was happened before you had phones, you know, for the, for the
caravan to go and to come back. Because again, this gets back
to the point that the same way before we saw we gave
him ninety days, so, you know, we want to give him time
that if we're about to do this that he actually can go
ahead and make the payment himself.
Okay, so so it's interesting because right because this אדרכתא adrachta is
what we write after the ninety days.
You would have thought that maybe when you write the פתיחא, pesicha,
the original thing, that that you know and then the ninety day
clock starts, that's when you want to sort of first inform him
because that's when you're giving him the ninety days to get the
property. But anyway here when we're about to seize the property we
have to inform him as well. כי הא דרבינא, Ki ha deRavina,
like the case of Ravina, שהא מר אחא תרי עסר ירחי שתא,
shala mar acha srei asar yarchei shata,
he waited a year for Mar Acha to get the information before
they were about to seize the property, עד דאזלא ואתיא שיירתא מבי
חוזאי, ad de'azla ve'asya shayrasa miBei Chuza'ei,
until the caravans went and came back from Bei Chuza'ei, and therefore
we normally so we give him a year presumably to get the
information to him and again it's interesting why we don't first get
the information and then wait the ninety days and then seize immediately
but anyway when we're ready to seize the property we give him
a year. ולא היא התם איניש אלימא הוה. Velo hi. Hasam inish
alima hava. There, the he was a very you know it's like
a strong-armed person. אי הוה מטי אדרכתא לידיה לא הוה אפשר לאפוקי
מיניה. Ee hava mati adrachta liyadeih lo hava efshar le'afokei mineih. In
that case if the if we would have given the litigant the
אדרכתא, adrachta, there would have been no way to reverse it. And
again here we're talking about the idea that the guy's claiming it's
a forgery, wants to be able to reverse it and so on.
So in that case we waited extra long before giving the guy
the writ of judgment, okay so that to give the guy yet
you know one final opportunity to come and to deal with the
case. But otherwise if we feel that we have the power to
reverse
it and then if something happens we'll be able to reverse it
again. Again, we after I'm still not getting because I it seems
you'd have to inform the guy first to wait the ninety days
but anyway.
Okay. אי הוה מטי אדרכתא לידיה לא הוה אפשר לאפוקי מיניה. Ee
hava mati adrachta liyadeih lo hava efshar le'afokei mineih. אבל הכא לא
כתבינן ליה אלא עד דאזיל שליחא בתלתא בשבתא, Aval hacha lo kasvinan
leh ella ad de'azil shelicha bislasa beshabsa, the messenger goes on Tuesday
because the court case is on a Monday, we remember we sort
of you know did a whole בה"ב, behab, ואתי בארבע בשבתא, ve'asya
be'arba beshabsa, and then he arrives to wherever he's going to inform
the guy on Wednesday, וחמישי בשבת קאי בדינא, vechamisha beshabsa kai bedina,
and then the guy has Thursday to come back. Okay, so again
what does that mean if the guy's more than three days away?
Right? So and and I'm still very confused because it seemed like
initially you know you didn't start the ninety day clock until the
guy could be informed and now we're sort of talking about you
know yet another waiting period and informing him before you're ready to
seize the property. Okay. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, now Ravina says, האי
שלוחא דרבנן מהימן ליה כבי תרי. hai shluacha deRabbanan meheman leh kebei
srei. Now if a שליח shliach if we send a messenger to
a guy and basically to tell him like you know you have
to go ahead and we're going back to the case of somebody
who doesn't want to show up to the court. Okay so we
sent a שליח shliach to get somebody somebody's being summoned to court
and the שליח shliach comes back and says he refuses to come.
And then because if he refuses to come as we've seen we're
going to start proceedings against him. So we believe the שליח, shaliach,
he doesn't have to bring witnesses. If we've appointed a שליח בית
דין shliach beis din then he's trusted to say the guy's refused
to come and there's we don't need any supporting evidence and then
we begin the proceedings against him and we write this שטר shtar
against him etc.
Seems like there's two moods here. Yeah. There's this waiting. And one
is that the בית דין beis din feels that it's in a
position of strength. Mm-hm. We can do whatever we want whenever we
want. So it's okay if we wait ninety days and then ninety
days.
Right, well, we're able to do right.
Or they feel they're in a position of weakness. Somebody can confuse
can refuse to come to the בית דין. beis din. It's like
they're bending over backwards to maintain their jurisdiction in the absence of
real power to.
Well what do you mean? I mean it wouldn't be wouldn't we
have to figure like now like what happens if somebody refuses a
subpoena or summons, right? So you know I mean or they issue
summary judgments against a person if they refuse to show to come
to court, right? So where you seeing that this is showing weakness?
Well I'm saying if in reality they didn't have all the power
that they claim to have. Right. Then it makes sense to bend
over backwards to stretch it out.
Oh I see. Maybe the giving of the time is not רחמנות
rachmanus on the other person but because we're not really certain that
we will be able to that could be that could be. Okay
so... All right, so מהימנא ליה כבי תרי, mehemnah lei kebei terei,
we trust him like two witnesses to say the guy's refusing to
come, and then we begin proceedings against this guy. ורמינא ליה לשמתא.
ve-remina lei le-shamta.
Now that's to put the guy in a חרם cherem as we
saw, then we give 90 days for him
to
like, well, it wasn't getting clear, is the 90 days for him
to then produce the money or is the חרם cherem in order
then to get him to start to come to court? But okay,
we put him under some type of a חרם cherem in order
to get him to come to court. אבל פתיחא, aval ptichah,
but this פתיחא, ptichah, which is actually the sort of
written חרם, cherem, which is what we referred to before. Okay, in
that case, כיון דממונא קא מחסר ליה, keivan de-mamona ka me-chasar lei,
so in that case it's going to cost him money. What's going
to cost him money? We'll see in a minute because he refused
and we wrote out this חרם cherem against him. In that case,
דקא בעי ליה למיתב ליה זוזי לספרא, de-ka ba'ei lei le-meitav lei
zuzei le-safra, because in the end when he sort of, you know,
does show up to court and so on, he has to pay
for the court costs of writing this חרם cherem against him. That's
part of the fine. Okay? So when we undo the חרם cherem
because he showed up and so on. So if we're going to,
to put him in חרם cherem because the שליח shliach says he
refuses to come to hold him in contempt of court, that we'll
do on the testimony of the שליח. shliach. But to actually write
out a court document where then we're going to charge him for
the court costs, that we're going to wait until there's some supporting
evidence that he refused to show up. לא, lo, we wouldn't do
it. אמר אבינא, amar Avina, יהבינן זימנא אפומא דאיתתא ואפומא דשיבבי. yehavinan
zimna apuma de-itata ve-apuma de-shivevei.
Now again, this idea of sort of that we're that we're sort
of saying that the person found out that he was being called
to court and he refused to come and then we're going to
start proceedings against him. Okay, so that would be not, you could
even send
a woman or neighbors. It doesn't have to be somebody who you
would normally use as a court officer. Okay, so basically, you know,
the guy isn't around and so you go ahead and you knock
on his neighbor's door and you say when ראובן Reuven comes back
from his, you know, from his business trip, tell him that he's
being summoned to court. Okay, or you tell his wife or you
send a woman to tell him or something. All those cases we're
going to assume that he'll get the information. And if he doesn't
show up on the appointed day, then he's going to be like
held in contempt and we're going to put a שמתא shamta on
him and we're going to begin proceedings against him. ולא אמרן אלא
דליתא במתא. ve-lo amran ala de-leita be-mata.
Now that's only if ראובן Reuven isn't in the city. Okay, then
we tell these people and we assume they live nearby him, they'll
inform him and that we'll assume they'll do what we told them
to do and he's going to get the message. אבל איתא במתא,
aval ita be-mata, if he is in the city, לא, lo, then
we don't trust them to get him the message. Why? דאמרינן, de-amrinan,
because they'll say אימר לא אמרו ליה. eimar lo amru lei. We
say they're not going to tell him. דאמרי, de-amri, because they'll say
אשתכח שליחא דבי דינא ואמר ליה. ashtechach shlicha de-bei dina ve-amar lei.
Hey, you know, ראובן Reuven is in the city, we're sure the
court found him on their own, you know, they don't need us
to go and tell him. So they don't take the weight of
their responsibility seriously if the court's in the city and ראובן Reuven
is in the city. But if ראובן Reuven isn't and they're the
neighbors and you say listen, you know, make sure as soon as
ראובן Reuven gets here that you tell him that we need to
see him and so on, then they take the responsibility seriously. Okay.
ולא אמרן אלא דלא חליף אבבא דבי דינא. ve-lo amran ala de-lo
chalif a-bava de-bei dina. And
even this, that we assume that they'll take this seriously, you know,
this agency, this job seriously, is only if ראובן Reuven doesn't normally
drop by בי דינא. bei dina. אבל חליף אבבא דבי דינא, aval
chalif a-bava de-bei dina, if he normally drops by בי דינא bei
dina when he sort of returns from his trips or wherever he's
coming when he comes into the city, לא, lo, then we don't
trust them to be the ones to tell him. Because אמרי, amri,
because
again they'll say, we're, the בי דינא bei dina doesn't need us
to tell ראובן. Reuven. אשתכח בי דינא ואמרו ליה. ashtechach bei dina
ve-amru lei.
They'll find him, they'll tell him. So it's only when they really
understand that it's all on them to do it that they'll, we
can assume that they'll do their job. ולא אמרן אלא דאתי ביומיה.
ve-lo amran ala de-ati be-yomei. And also we can only trust them
to have informed him if he's going to be returning that day.
אבל לא אתי ביומיה, aval lo ati be-yomei, if he's not going
to be returning that day from whatever trip he's on, לא, lo,
then we don't trust that they've told him. אימר אישתלויי אישתלו. eimar
ishtaluyei ishtalu.
They forgot. Okay, yeah, by the time it's a few days later
they don't remember, they're not, you know, it slipped their mind. So
again, all of this is in order to give a little more
רחמנות rachmanus to ראובן, Reuven, because if we assume ראובן Reuven got
the message and he hasn't shown up to the בי דינא, bei
dina, we're going to start proceedings against him. So can we trust
that he got the message, you know, in these cases? And only
under narrow circumstances can we assume he's got the message. Okay. אמר
רבא, amar Rava, האי מאן דכתבו עליה פתיחא, hai man de-katvu alei
ptichah, so somebody who has been given like
this,
again this
פתיחא ptichah is like this writ of contempt because he has not
shown up to judgment, עד דאתי לדינא לא מקרעינן ליה, ad de-ati
le-dina lo makreinan lei, until he actually shows up to judgment we
do not tear up that writ against him. put his putting in
חרם. cherem. Even if he says, "I'm coming, I'm coming," we don't
say, we don't trust him that he's actually going to show up
and we don't cancel the judgment against the writ of חרם cherem
against him until he actually shows up. But if we're writing a
writ against him על דלא ציית לדינא al delo tzyas ledina that
he's not
actually following through on the judgment, the judgment was he owes a
thousand dollars and he's been hesitating and not paying up the guy,
and therefore we're going to write this writ against him, so in
that case עד דציית לא מקרעינן ליה, ad detzyas lo makrinan lei,
then similarly we won't tear it up until he actually pay up
the money. Even if he says, "I'm going to pay up the
money." Okay, which seems very reasonable. If the guy's been postponing and
resisting and so on, then we need to use this... then we're
not going to trust him and give up our only leverage against
him until he actually produces. Why do you say that? Because interestingly,
because then the גמרא's Gemara going to reject it. It would seem
completely reasonable, right? I mean, but then the last line is ולא
היא. velo hi. כיון דאמר צייתנא מקרעינן ליה. keivan de’amar tzyasna makrinan
lei.
As soon as he says, "Fine, I'll give the money," like he's
not obviously resisting, we trust him. Now why is that different than
in the other case if he says, "I'm going to show up"?
So רש"י Rashi says, well if he says he's going to show
up, then show up. But if you say you're going to pay
the money, there could be reasons why you're still not doing it
immediately, like maybe you have to actually raise the money in order
to pay it. And meaning that there are different reasons, meaning it's
not contempt. It's like the גמרא Gemara said before, before you came
here there was a whole discussion about giving somebody ninety days to
collect the money that,
if you're not coming to court right away, clearly it's because you're
rejecting our authority and you're refusing to participate. If you're not paying
right away, it might be because you have to collect the money.
But the difference is, but that's... if from the get-go you said,
"Yes I'm going to pay, give me time to collect the money,"
we would understand. But if from the beginning you said, "I refuse
to pay, I reject, I reject," and then you said, "Okay fine
I will," and then you... then it's like we should be skeptical
about whether, right? So you do understand why in one case it
does take time, it might take time even if you're willing to
participate but not why we would trust you after you've been resisting.
Not really, because the גמרא Gemara before was saying that he's given
time because he's bringing witnesses, right? So both things started because can
you do it with... listen to witnesses שלא בפני בעל דין? shelo
bifnei ba’al din? Right. So I think the assumption was if he
needs time, it's to find a witness or find the evidence
that's contrary to the
witnesses.
So there is a good reason, just like you have to raise
the money you might have to raise the evidence.
Yeah, again, I hear that. I guess I'm still not certain. It
was not clear to me whether the גמרא Gemara was consistently in
that framing or whether it was sort of shifting to more general
rules of court proceedings of people that are refusing to show up.
That was the sense that I got. And if it's like you,
that the guy's saying, "I need time to produce the witnesses," then
it's not clear this distinction the גמרא's Gemara making at the end
and why, right? So my sense was at a certain stage we
shifted to be talking about like general people who are in contempt
of court and not showing up. But yeah.
Why should someone care about this order?
Yeah,
so שמתא shamta is like a light חרם, cherem, but it basically
means... it has consequences, social consequences, right? It means
that people don't engage with business with him and it's... so yeah.
I mean, so that was like the power that the court had
before it actually used... had to use like actual physical force was
these types of forms of חרם. cherem.
So it's not like, we'll just keep it in the file and
we won't...
Right, exactly. Exactly. Look, it's a whole issue that comes up today
with עגונה agunah cases, right? And at what stage should they sort
of write that somebody is in contempt and then whatever they have
the power to do, whether they're going to do it. Okay. So
now we continue. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, כותבין זמן בשני
ובחמישי ובשני, kosvin zman besheini uvechamishi uvesheini, זימנא וזימנא בתר זימנא. zimna
vezimna batar zimna. Okay. ולמחר כתבינן. ulemachar kasvinan.
So we give the guy שני חמישי ושני. sheini chamishi vesheini.
Now the case here is רש"י Rashi says, hold on,
let me just check רש"י. Rashi. ליום שני בשבת אם לא יבוא.
leyom sheini beshabbos im lo yavo.
Right. So again, this now is clearly another case about a person
that's just generally in contempt. He refuses to show up. He's being
summoned to דין. din. And again the question is if he continues
to refuse to summon, then again, either we issue some writ of
contempt against him and or, based on the סוגיא sugya earlier, we'll
even start proceedings against him. Okay. So how much time do we
give him before we actually issue some writ of contempt? So he
says we call him for בית דין beis din for Monday, presumably
they start new cases on Monday, and then and then Thursday, and
then Monday again. We give him multiple opportunities. ולמחר ulemachar and after
the end of the third Monday, of the second Monday, the third
opportunity, כתבינן kasvinan then we write this writ of שמתא shamta against
him. This writ of contempt. רב אסי איקלע לבי רב כהנא. Rav
Assi ikla levei Rav Kahana. Rav
Assi dropped by to the house or maybe the בית דין beis
din of Rav Kahana. חזא ההיא איתתא chaza hahei ittasa
and he saw that there was a case of a woman דאזמנוה
לדינא de’azimnuha ledina that she was summoned to court בפניא befanya in
the evening ובצפרא uvetzafra and in the
morning. in the afternoon and by the צפרא tsafra by the next
morning כתב עלה פתיחא kasav ala p'tikha
he wrote a writ of contempt against her, not a writ of
judgment, a writ of contempt. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so she just
because she didn't show on one day, לא סבר לה מר להא
דאמר רב חסדא lo savar lah Mar l'ha d'amar Rav Chisda קובעין
זמן שני וחמישי ושני kovin zman sheni va-chamishi ve-sheni that you give
somebody like, you know, a Monday, Thursday, Monday before you write a
writ of contempt for them not showing up? אמר ליה, Amar lei,
הני מילי גברא דאניס, hani mili gavra de-anis, that's about a man
because, you know, we understand that he might have other things that
are preventing him from coming to court, right? Because he's got a
job, he's got to go on a business
trip ולא איתא במתא ve-la isa be-masa he's not always in the
city. אבל איתתא, Aval iteta, but a woman, כיון דאיתא במתא keivan
de-isa be-masa she's always at home, so ולא אתיא ve-lo asa and
if she's not showing up מורדת היא moredes hi she's obviously rebelling
against the authority of the court. So, you can just say what
you want. Is that an accurate description of reality? Is there a
certain type of obviously a negative view of women in this? I
don't know what to say about that. I mean, one assumed that
women had jobs at home too, but I guess the point is
is that maybe there's a presumption that they can always arrange their
affairs more than a man can. Let's hear from the women in
the שיעור. shiur. I mean I know this is hilarious, but
but it's funny because when we think about I want I don't
know what the גמרא's Gemara reasoning for why women aren't חייב chayav
in תפילה. tefillah.
Right. But like how you think of it as it's the opposite
that like men do have time to do תפילה tefillah and women
are busy with other stuff. Aha. So it's fascinating they're like women
don't have time to talk to God, but they got to go
to court.
Oh, I see. That's a real interesting contrast. Right. It's interesting.
I mean what the גמרא's Gemara really doing here though.
But there is I just want to just say in today's society,
there is some truth to that. Like if a guy has a
job, I mean, okay, it could be the woman has a job
and the guy stays at home, but still it's more common, right,
the guy has a job and the woman stays at home and
then something has to happen, the kid has to get picked up
from school because he's sick, there's just a presumption that the woman
is going to do it whatever was on her schedule and not
and not the man who's at work. What?
I said as opposed to that as I...
Right, but I'm saying that's the same assumption, right. The woman can
accommodate her schedule, I'm at work, you know?
So, right, yeah, so what's really going on here though is is
that who is it? חסדא, Chisda, he's he's changing the rule based
on circumstances, right? Doesn't go, here's the rule. Right? But he's saying
well, okay, but because the circumstances dictate that maybe, you know, women
are always in town, then the rule's different.
So
just the fact that we don't have a hard and fast rule
about it, that we're willing to
interpret the
rule based on circumstances, right.
That is correct.
Okay, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav
Yehuda, לא יהבינן זימנא לא
ביומי ניסן ולא ביומי תשרי. lo yahvinan zimna lo be-yomei Nisan ve-lo
be-yomei Tishrei.
We do not summon somebody to court and then have them have
to suffer the consequences during the ניסן Nisan which is the harvest
season, and תשרי Tishrei which is the planting season. People have other
priorities during the harvest season and planting season. It's not fair to
summon them to court, and presumably even if we did, we wouldn't
hold them in contempt if they didn't show up, although he doesn't
say that. Okay, אבל מניסן לבתר יומי ניסן aval mi-Nisan le-basar yomei
Nisan
but we could send them a summons during the spring, during the
during the harvest season, that they should come to court after ניסן
Nisan is over. וביומי תשרי לבתר יומי תשרי u-be-yomei Tishrei le-basar yomei
Tishrei or during the again, doesn't literally mean תשרי, Tishrei, that's why
it says יומי תשרי, yomei Tishrei, right? The planting season, that they
should come to court afterwards הוינן. havinan. Now, ממעלי שבתא לבתר מעלי
שבתא לא הוינן. mi-malei Shabbos le-basar malei Shabbos lo havinan. We do
not send them a summons on Friday to come up to come
to court after שבת Shabbos to like on a Monday. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? מעבידתא דשבתא טרידי. mi-avadta de-Shabbos tridei.
A person is too busy getting ready for שבת Shabbos and not
paying attention to your summons. Yeah, yeah, whatever, fine, I'm I'm in
a rush. Okay, so it's just that people don't really hear the
summons if you summon them on a Friday. אמר רב נחמן, Amar
Rav Nachman, לא יהבינן זימנא לא לבני כלה בכלה ולא לבני ריגלא
בריגלא. lo yahvina zimna lo livnei kala be-kala ve-lo livnei rigla be-rigla.
We do not summon the people that coming to the כלה. kala.
The כלה kala is the דרשה drasha on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, we
don't summon them like, oh, everybody's showing up, right? Here's all the
people I've been trying to to get to come to court, right?
I couldn't find this guy, so it's the perfect opportunity to go
ahead and to issue a summons on him and to summon him
to go, which is interesting question of isn't that like דובר דבר
dover davar to be issuing summons on שבת. Shabbos. But anyway, רש"י
Rashi says כלה kala here means שבת, Shabbos,
it's it's the ירחי כלה yarchei kalla which is the period before
the רגל, regel, but that's the next thing, לבני ריגלא. livnei rigla.
רש"י Rashi says here כלה kala רש"י Rashi says is דברים לשמוע
הדרשה בכל שבת. dvarim lishmoa ha-drasha be-chol Shabbos. Okay, so
for the ones that come to the sermon, okay, ולא לבני ריגלא
בריגלא ve-lo livnei rigla be-rigla
or the people that gather for the learning prior to a רגל,
regel, you don't summon them, you know, you know when they come
on the not whether the רגל regel means the רגל regel itself
or whether it means the period before the רגל regel when they
all gather to learn תורה, Torah, you don't say great, we got
you all here, here are the... summons were issued against you. That's
not going to help attendance for the next time around. And also
it's a little off-side anyway. כי אתו לקמיה דרב נחמן, Ki avasu
lekamei d'Rav Nachman, now
when people would come for רב נחמן Rav Nachman for a דרשה,
drasha, I'm sorry, ואתו לקמיה, v'asu lekamei,
I'm sorry, אתו לקמיה asu lekamei meaning the שליחי בית דין, shlichei
beis din, right, or no רש״י Rashi says תובעין, tovim, excuse me,
the litigants, they would come to רב נחמן Rav Nachman and they
would say, 'רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, you got all these people in
your audience now, they've been hiding out from us, we'd like to,
you know, use this opportunity to summon them to court, you know,
and to issue right there whatever it is, a warrant, not a
warrant, what is it they issue? A subpoena, right? You know when
you know they always have those things like you try to find
somebody to give them the subpoena because they've been avoiding you. So
this was the opportunity to give these guys their subpoenas. So let's
do it.' So he would say to them, אמר להו בחילא דדחקי
כנופייכו, Amar lehu b'cheila d'dachki knuphaichu,
what, you think I gathered them all together to serve your purposes
so we could do this to them? I gathered them together to
teach them תורה, Torah, it's not fair to them and, you know,
obviously would hurt his business in the future. Okay. והאידנא דאיכא רמאי
חששינן. V'idna d'ika ramai chashinan.
Nowadays however that there are deceptive people, we are concerned. I didn't
understand that. Who's being deceptive? People come to the דרשה drasha and
they don't really want to hear the דרשה? drasha? I mean coming
doesn't make you avoid the, like I don't understand what that means.
Meaning the judgment. What? Meaning people avoiding the
the judgment and therefore what do we do? What?
It's another way to find them.
Oh, oh, oh, meaning because it is so hard in general to
find them and this is the only opportunity. Ah, I see. Okay
fine. Okay, if now that it's so hard and people really manage
to avoid, this is the only opportunity, we do it. Of course
what that does to your attendance I don't know, but you know
they tell stories by the way about how, you know, in certain
places they managed to find people that were,
what do you call it, skipping out on parole or have been
avoiding warrants or whatever, that they would send, like,
like letters to, you know, their last known address or people they
knew were associated with them addressed to them as sort of like,
you know, 'You just won a free trip to Disneyland, you have
to show up to this place in order to claim your gift.'
And then they would actually manage to issue a lot of warrants
at the time so people would show up. What? Different Disneyland. Exactly.
All right. Okay, moving back to the משנה Mishnah and just repeating
the thing we said before on the משנה. Mishnah. מה דבר שיש
בו אחריות חייב לשלם, Ma d'avar sheyesh bo achrayus chayav l'shalem,
if this thing that was stolen and now the kids have it
after the father died has אחריות, achrayus, they have to pay. And
that meant one of two things. Either it meant that the גזילה
gezeila is not around but the father left property and therefore there
are liens on the property on the real estate. Or what we've
been saying it means, a very unusual reading of the משנה, Mishnah,
which we're going to say again. מתני ליה רבי לרבי שמעון בריה,
Masni lei Rebbe l'Rebbe Shimon brei, רבי Rebbe taught this to רבי
שמעון Rebbe Shimon his son. לא דבר שיש בו אחריות ממש אלא
אפילו פרה וחורש בה, Lo davar sheyesh bo achrayus mamash ella afilu
parah v'choresh bah,
but we don't literally mean land. We mean anything that is sort
of like obvious and public, even though technically the kids own it
because it would be like יאוש ושינוי רשות yeush v'shinui reshus or
whatever reasons we gave, but if it's very obvious, oh look, this
guy, they're plowing, you know, with that stolen cow, then you return
it, you know, for כבוד אביהם. kevod avihem. I would even think
כבוד עצמם, kevod atzmam, but okay. פרה וחורש בה חמור ומחמר אחריו,
Parah v'choresh bah chamor u'mechamer acharay, or a donkey that they're now
using and leading afterwards. חייבין להחזיר מפני כבוד אביהם, Chayavin l'hachzir mipnei
kevod avihem, they have to return it. בעי מיניה רב כהנא מרב,
Ba'ei minei Rav Kahana m'Rav, רב כהנא Rav Kahana asked רב. Rav.
מיטה ומסב עליה, Mita u'mesaiv aleha,
let's say it's something that is you used regularly but you don't
use outdoors, you use indoors. Is that considered public enough that you
would have to return? A bed that you recline on, like for
eating, שולחן ואוכל עליו, shulchan v'ochel alav, or the table that you
eat off of. מהו? mahu? What's the story? Because people come to
your house and see it but it's not the same public aspect.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him back then, תן לחכם
ויחכם עוד. Ten l'chacham v'yichkam od. Yeah, a smart person should be
able to figure it out for himself. Okay, which is okay, which
way does it go? So רש״י Rashi says, well, presumably it means
yeah, it's the same thing, so figures, you know, not exactly the
same thing, but whatever, we don't have to spell everything out. All
right, moving on to the next משנה. Mishnah. Now things get really
interesting. אין פורטין
לא מתיבת המוכסין ולא מכיס של גבאי. Ein pordin lo m'teivas hamochsin
v'lo m'kis shel gabbai. You cannot change money from the box of
tax collectors or the pouch of גבאי, gabbai, which is a different
type of tax collectors. Now in the Roman world there was something
called tax farming, which basically meant that they privatized tax collection. That
the government would basically say, 'Okay, we can expect to get revenues
of like if we did our job or whatever, you know, I
don't know, we would gross a million dollars from this locality, so
we'll sell that to you for five hundred thousand dollars and then
you have to go ahead and you have to, you know, administer
it and do the actual collecting and so on.' Saves us the
effort, saves us etc. Now the only problem with that is, you
go, what? And you keep the money you collect. The only problem
is is that if we're not doing a good job supervising it,
you could obviously abuse the privilege and collect more than you should
be collecting. So there was a general perception that the tax collectors
were all גנבים ganavim because they were all collecting outside of the
bounds of what they should legitimately be collecting. You know, when, when
Jesus eats with the tax, what he he eats with the, doesn't
he eat with the tax collectors there? Right, it's the same thing.
Like these were perceived of, it was the prostitutes and the tax
collectors, right, this was like the low part of society for different
reasons, but whatever. And the tax collectors were very wealthy but they
were considered to be גנבים ganavim or גזלנים. gazlanim. So because the
money in there so that they had was seen essentially as money
that they collected excessive of what they were entitled to, it was
seen as that they were you know stolen money in their pouches.
So if you go ahead and you change your coins, you say
oh, can you break a 20, and you say it to the
tax collector, so then he's giving you money that is stolen money.
Now תוספות Tosfos asks, is this technically a problem that it's like,
you know, money that the owners are not מיאש mitya'esh on it?
I mean, it's a little bit hard to imagine that they're not
מיאש mitya'esh on money that they pay to the tax collectors that
has the backing of the government, right? So I mean, so even
so, one could say they weren't מיאש mitya'esh somehow, they hope to
get it back, and therefore you're holding onto somebody else's money that
belongs to the guy who paid the taxes. But more likely, תוספות
Tosfos says even if they were מיאש mitya'esh and even if it
was יאוש ושינוי רשות, ye'ush v'shinui reshus, it is very unseemly for
you to be taking money from what is perceived to be essentially
stolen—stolen goods and stolen money. Okay, so if you take a look
at תוספות, Tosfos, אין פורטין לא מתיבת המוכסין, ein pordin lo mi-teivas
ha-mochsin,
תוספות Tosfos says like this: לרבנן דאמרי סתם גזילה לא הוי
יאוש בעלים אתי שפיר, le-rabbanan de-amri stam gezeila lo havi ye'ush ba'alim
ati shapir, that it makes sense. Of course, even if סתם גזילה
stam gezeila is not יאוש, ye'ush, I think this is a little
bit more than סתם גזילה. stam gezeila. Anyway, ומכל מקום קתני—or u-mikol
makom katani
we'll get to the next line, but let's read the next line
in the משנה. Mishnah. So you don't change your money with the
tax collectors ואין נוטלין מהם צדקה, ve-ein notlin meihem tzedakah, you don't
take צדקה tzedakah money from them because it's assumed to be stolen,
אבל נוטל הוא מתוך ביתו או מן השוק. aval notel hu mi-toch
beito o min ha-shuk.
But you
can—but you can if they're actually, it's not that, you know,
you see the guy at home and you knock on his door
and say can you break a 20 for me, or you see
him in the marketplace and he's not going around collecting his taxes,
okay, in that case you don't have to assume that all money
he has on him is stolen if it's not coming directly out
of, you know, the pouch of the box in which he puts
the tax money, okay, because then the other money you don't have
to assume is stolen that he has. And the first line in
the גמרא Gemara is תנא אבל נותנין לו דינר ונותנין לו את
השאר. tanna aval nosin lo dinar ve-nosin lo es ha-sh'ar. If your
taxes is a 20 dollars or whatever, you can give him—a ten
dollars—you can give him a 20 and take ten dollars in change,
okay, even though he's giving you the ten dollars in change out
of that pouch. So now if you look, so רש"י Rashi says
basically it's like מציל מידם, matzil mi-yadam, right, you know, I mean,
what are you going to do? You're going to have to be
allow yourself to if you refuse to take your change, right, so
no, you don't have to lose your own money just because of
this concern. So let's take a look at תוספות Tosfos about this:
לרבנן דאמרי—back le-rabbanan de-amri to תוספות, Tosfos, אין פורטין—לרבנן דאמרי סתם גזילה
gezeila לא הוי יאוש yeush. בעלים אתי שפיר, that it
makes
sense because it's really stolen funds that are in his pouch. Okay,
ומכל מקום, u-mikol makom, I mean it still is considered belonging to
the original owner. ומכל מקום קתני דנושא דינר ויחזיר לו השאר, u-mikol
makom katani di-nosei dinar ve-yachazir lo ha-sh'ar,
so if it really is money that still belongs to the original
owner, why can you take your change? So he says הואיל ואין
ידוע בבירור שהגזל, ho'il ve-ein yadua b'virur she-gezel,
not necessarily all the money is גזל, gezel, I mean some of
it he was legitimately collecting, so you don't have to, you know,
so you can be a little bit lenient if it's just about
protecting, you know, not being even more stolen from yourself. Okay, so
that's assuming that the re—that it really is still considered owned by
the original owners. ורבי שמעון נמי דאמר סתם גזילה הוי יאוש בעלים,
ve-Rabbi Shimon nami de-amar stam gezeila havi ye'ush ba'alim, and even if
we assume that normal גזילה the owners do give up, and what
I would set to say is that should be presumed to be
the case here, right, because I mean, my god, it's a tax
collector. דהשתא הוה ליה יאוש ושינוי רשות, de-hastha havlei ye'ush ve-shinui reshus,
so now what's the problem? You'll take possession of it, it'll be
יאוש ושינוי רשות. ye'ush v'shinui reshus. מכל מקום אין פורטין משום דדבר
מגונה הוא, mikol makom ein pordin mishum de-davar meguneh hu, it's this,
you know, it's disgusting,
it's despicable, דתיבה וכיס מיוחדת
להצניע שם גזילות, de-teiva ve-kis miyuchedes le-hatznia sham gezelos, that exactly that,
you know, receptacle in which you put all your stolen goods in,
again this is tax money, but you know, all your stolen goods
שלהם ודרכו כל שעה ולהצניע שם. she-lahem ve-darko kol sha'ah u-le-hatznia sham.
I mean, this is the place, this is like the גזל gezel
box, and you're taking stuff out of it. So even if technically,
you know,
it's—first of all, you could also say like we—which we haven't really
explored, right, if Dov here steals something and I know that Jenna
was מיאש, mitya'esh, am I allowed to take it from him even
as a—first of all, there's a question can I buy it from
him because then I'm providing a market and I'm supporting it, and
that's the גמרא Gemara will get to it. Okay, but let's even
say I'm not buying, can I take it from him as a
gift? My receiving it as a gift is—is making it leave Jenna's
רשות, reshus, right, like even though I will own it at the
end, my participating effects it completely leaving her control. But even besides
that, תוספות Tosfos says look, the bottom part here is that this
whole thing is inappropriate, you know, it's very much perceived of as
that this is—this is stolen funds, technically whether you'll own it in
the end or not own it in the end, are the owners
מיאש, mitya'esh, you're taking stuff that is seen of as like taking
stolen funds, which then raises a really interesting question about that line
about צדקה, tzedakah, which of course every שול shul rabbi and every
Jewish institution would have to worry about, which is a lot of
people who make their money in unseemly fashions, you know, want to
then sort of— you know, salve their conscience or whatever by making
major donations to צדקה tzedakah and to Jewish causes, and do you
say like, 'Oh, I can't take it because it's all from ill-gotten
gains?' And maybe you also want to say I'm indirectly helping this
person like rationalize all the stuff that they do and go ahead
on the other hand it's like why not at least some good
should come out of all the bad they are doing. We should
help support my important cause. Believe me, a lot of Jewish a
lot of a lot of my a lot a lot of a
lot of a lot of a lot of rabbis and a lot
of Jewish institutions have accepted money from nefarious
that have been you know ill-gotten gains. Anyway there's an interesting discussion
in the ראשונים Rishonim and in the פוסקים Poskim about this, but
you see that the משנה Mishnah is reading it narrowly. You don't
take it from the pouch of the stolen money. I can go
to the guy's house and the money the stuff he has there
was clearly bought from his profits, but as long as I'm not
taking it directly out of the pouch it's allowed. So, you know,
so on the one hand it says don't, but on the other
hand it narrows it to very much to when it's like the
most directly engage you know participating in the act itself, you know
directly engaging with the actual stolen goods themselves. So that's the case
of the משנה. Mishnah. So let's take a look at the גמרא
Gemara now. Now the גמרא Gemara turns to a broader discussion
about the issue this issue about the tax collectors are considered to
be גזלנים. gazlanim. Okay, ומוכסים, u'mochsim, so tax collectors. So the גמרא
Gemara says ואמר שמואל, ve'amar Shmuel,
but one minute, why are tax collectors a problem? Doesn't שמואל Shmuel
say דינא דמלכותא דינא? dina demalchuta dina?
The rule of the government is the rule, the rule of the
kingdom is the rule. So if the kingdom gives the person the
power to collect, it should be legitimate.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב חנינא בר כהנא אמר שמואל
במוכס שאין לו קצבה. amar Rav Chanina bar Kahana amar Shmuel be'moches
she'ein lo kitzvah.
He doesn't follow he doesn't go by the actual rules, okay? He
basically collects more than he's entitled to based on the rules on
what the government has allowed him. To which makes which clearly was
a major concern. דבי רבי ינאי אמרי במוכס העומד מאליו. devei Rabbi
Yannai amrei be'moches ha'omed mei'elav.
He actually was not appointed by the government. Okay, he is the
local mafioso. He's saying that he's collecting protection money or whatever he's
doing and no government backs him and so that really is גזל.
gezel. Now by the way the important the thing that all the
scholars point out is that all of the well you know let's
read this also and then I'll make the point. Okay so the
גמרא Gemara says איכא דמתני לה אהא, ika de'matni lah aha, some
teach this discussion on the following משנה כלאים. Mishnah Kilayim. לא ילבש
אדם כלאים אפילו על גבי עשרה בגדים. lo yilbash adam Kilayim afilu
al gabei asara begadim.
Do not wear clothes that are כלאים Kilayim even on top of
ten garments, so you're not
directly getting like physical warmth benefit from it, it's not a normal
way of wearing it. להבריח בו את המכס. lehavriach bo et hamoches.
So and you know even the reason you would be doing it
and you might think it's allowed from a כלאים Kilayim perspective is
you're doing it to get out of paying tax. Why? Because apparently
you would only have to pay like import taxes on stuff that
were like wares that you were bringing in, but anything that you
were wearing wares anyway you know goods that you were bringing in
but anything you were wearing on your person would not be taxed.
Okay? So don't go ahead and try to put ten garments on
your person and one of them is כלאים Kilayim even to even
if it's a legitimate reason like to get out of taxes, you
can't do it because of כלאים Kilayim concerns. So the גמרא Gemara
says מתניתין דלא כרבי עקיבא, matnitin de'lo k'Rabbi Akiva, this משנה Mishnah
is not like Rabbi Akiva. דתניא, detanya, as shown in a ברייתא,
Braitah, אסור להבריח את המכס. assur lehavriach et hamoches.
You cannot go ahead and avoid paying your these excise taxes. רבי
שמעון אומר משום רבי עקיבא מותר להבריח את המכס. Rabbi Shimon omer
mishum Rabbi Akiva mutar lehavriach et hamoches. You're allowed to get out
of paying taxes. Okay these again these are like import taxes. בשלמא
לענין כלאים בהא קמיפלגי. bishlama le'inyan Kilayim beha kamiflegi. So when it
comes to כלאים Kilayim this is the debate. It's interesting that we
didn't even say a debate about כלאים, Kilayim, but anyway this is
the issue that would come up by כלאים Kilayim about wearing it
in this context. דמר סבר דבר שאינו מתכוין מותר. demar savar davar
she'eino mitkavein mutar. If you're wearing it not to serve as a
garment but just as a way of getting out of these taxes,
is that considered like so you're getting benefit from the wearing it
of clothes but it's not you're not intending to. So it's like
or you're doing an act of wearing כלאים Kilayim but not really
intending to. That's a funny type of an אינו מתכוין. eino mitkavein.
A normal אינו מתכוין eino mitkavein is like by שבת Shabbat is
I'm walking across this garden and I'm trying to get to the
other side but because of the cleats on my shoe I'm going
to make a furrow in the yard. I'm not even aware or
trying to do the other act. Here you're totally aware of the
act that you're doing. You're putting כלאים Kilayim on your back. You
just conceptually are not conceptualizing it as an act of wearing, you're
sort of conceptualizing it as I'm carrying it but I'm carrying it
in this way to get out of. So it's interesting that the
גמרא Gemara calls this an אינו מתכוין, eino mitkavein, it's not our
סוגיא sugya right now. Well הנאה לשמה, hana'ah lishmah, right?
I mean you're eating it but you're not
right,
you're not eating it in a way you could say like I'm
not getting הנאת לבישה hana'at levishah out of it or something. Right.
So why exactly does the phrase אינו מתכוין eino mitkavein is interesting
and how much anyway like is this about yeah, so anyway but
right but let's just leave it at that. So one says even
though So one says even though that wasn't exactly your intent to
be wearing it constitutes wearing it, ומר, u'mar, ומר, u'mar, now
one says because it wasn't your intention it's not really an act
of wearing. ומר סבר דבר שאין מתכוון אסור, u'mar savar davar she'ein
miskavein assur, it doesn't matter whether that was your intention or not,
you're still wearing it, it's still a problem. Whatever, we could debate
the כלאים kilayim issue. אבל אבריח המכס מי שרי? aval avriach hamoches
mi sharei?
Now, but how could Rabbi Akiva say you're allowed to cheat the
taxes? והאמר שמואל דינא דמלכותא דינא, veha'amar Shmuel dina d'malchusa dina,
you go by the law of the government. Notice Rabbi Akiva is
a תנא, Tanna, Shmuel here is an אמורא. Amora. All of the
evidence that feels that it's okay to get out of paying taxes
and these tax collectors are גזלנים gazlanim or whatever is all Tannaitic.
Okay, but how does that work with Shmuel's statement? So the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר רב חנינא בר כהנא אמר שמואל במוכס שאין לו
קצבה, amar Rav Chanina bar Kahana amar Shmuel b'moches she'ein lo kitzvah,
it's a tax collector that goes beyond the right parameters, he does
whatever he wants. דבי רבי ינאי אמרי במוכס העומד מאליו, debei Rabbi
Yannai amrei b'moches ha'omed mei'elav, he's not even backed by the government.
Okay, ואיכא דמתני הכא, ve'ika d'masni hacha, others say this same discussion
on this third Tannaitic source.
נודרין להרגין ולחרמין ולמוכסין שהיא תרומה שהיא בית המלך. nodrin l'hargin u'lecharamin
u'lemochsin she'hi terumah she'hi beis hamelech. Basically, you're there and you're carrying
all of these goods and you're stopped by a tax collector and
they make you pay whatever it is, the import tax, the export
tax for all the goods you're carrying and you say, no, no,
no, these are tax-free. Why are they tax-free? Because they all belong
to the king or they're all תרומה. terumah. Somehow the tax collectors
gave you a free pass for תרומה. terumah. I don't know. Okay.
Now, I don't believe you, you're lying. So you say, no, I'll
take a נדר, neder, all the fruit
in the world is אסור assur to me if this does not
belong to בית המלך. beis hamelech. Okay, okay, fine, you're telling the
truth, and he lets you go. And you're of course, you are
lying. Okay, so the way the משנה Mishnah explains it what you
do is in your mind you sort of say I have my
fingers crossed essentially, which is what you said in your mind, I
said all the fruit in the world is אסור assur to me
היום hayom today, but you didn't articulate the היום hayom part. Okay,
and the משנה Mishnah says that you're allowed to do that and
that's not a problem about making a false נדר, neder, even though
normally דברים שבלב אינם דברים, devarim shebalev einam devarim, here because you
were sort of pressured to say it, there's an understanding that, you
know, you didn't really mean it, at least an understanding of, we
understand, the tax collector didn't understand that. Okay, anyway, so that's the
point of the משנה Mishnah that says it's not a נדר neder
problem. You can take this נדר neder to the הרגין hargin murderers
who are demanding your property, or חרמין charamin or מוכסין. mochsin. חרמין
charamin are other types of, whatever, רש"י Rashi says, oh just
I don't know, robbers, רש"י Rashi says, okay, or tax collectors. Okay,
and you can say that it's תרומה terumah or belongs to the
king, אף על פי שאינו תרומה אף על פי שאינו של בית
המלך. af al pi she'eino terumah af al pi she'eino shel beis
hamelech. Okay, and it's not a problem about a נדר neder because
in your mind you're thinking היום, hayom, and even though normally we
don't go by דברים שבלב, devarim shebalev, because of the context here
we do go by דברים שבלב. devarim shebalev. Okay, so all that's
a נדר neder הלכה, halacha, but how are you allowed to steal
from the
מוכס? moches? ולמוכס? u'lemoches? How can you steal from the מוכס? moches?
האמר שמואל דינא דמלכותא דינא. ha'amar Shmuel dina d'malchusa dina. שמואל Shmuel
says דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina d'malchusa dina, so how could you be
doing this from a, just a, you know, from a גזל gezel
standpoint? אמר רב חנינא בר כהנא אמר שמואל במוכס שאין לו קצבה,
amar Rav Chanina bar Kahana amar Shmuel b'moches she'ein lo kitzvah, he
doesn't have any limits. דבי רבי ינאי אמרי במוכס העומד מאליו, debei
Rabbi Yannai amrei b'moches ha'omed mei'elav,
he's not really appointed by the government. Okay, now before we go
on, you'll notice all three examples were Tannaitic. All the תנאים, Tannaim,
Tannaitic sources assume that מוכסין mochsin are גזלנים gazlanim and are illegitimate.
שמואל Shmuel is an אמורא Amora and he's an אמורא Amora from
בבל. Bavel. So what the academics point out is, is that, you
know, the Babylonian government, the Persian government was much more, we know
this, they were much more hospitable to the Jews, they much more
had a just type of a legal system, and שמואל Shmuel was
very close to שבור מלכא Shvor Malka who was the head of
the, you know, Persian government and whatever, and therefore שמואל Shmuel said
like, you know, this is a legitimate government and we have to
follow the laws, you know. So he was the one that articulated
דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina d'malchusa dina. The fact that it was not
perceived that way by the Jews living in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
under the oppressive Roman government, you know, and they sort of saw
the whole thing as illegitimate, right, so that's really, and the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi never says דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina d'malchusa dina, it's a pure
בבלי Bavli שמואל Shmuel type of a statement. Okay, so it's interesting,
right, that the גמרא Gemara is trying to reconcile them, but they're
coming from very different perceptions of the government. It's sort of like
רב משה Rav Moshe has a תשובה Teshuvah that he was asked
by, you know, some,
like by some ישיבות Yeshivos about can they, it's either, I know
there was one question back, can you cheat on your Regents? And
there was another question about are you basically allowed to sort of
lie in order to get government subsidies? And all these wonderful things.
Of course רב משה Rav Moshe starts the תשובה Teshuvah by saying
חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, it's all like, it's all total לשון הרע,
lashon hara, no real ישיבה Yeshiva would ever even be asking this
question, but to answer it in theory at least, right, and then
what he basically says is, he says, you know, he says, we
live in a מדינה של חסד medina shel chesed that all they
want is for the good of their citizens and חס ושלום chas
v'shalom that we should ever think that we should ever try, you
know, do anything deceptive and misrepresentative and so on. You know, what
he's basically saying is, hey guys, you don't live in Czarist Russia
anymore, like under oppressive Czarist Russia maybe the whole mentality was whatever
you can, you know, because whatever you can manage to cheat out
of, not to cheat, like to get out of the government since
the government is stealing. everything from you anyway, right? Whatever devious devices
you can use, that's legitimate. He says it's very different here, but
it requires a very different mentality to accept that's a different reality
of the government under which you live. So anyway שמואל Shmuel says
דינא דמלכותא דינא. Dina Demalchuta Dina. That was not the perception of
the תנאים Tanna'im in regards to the sort of Roman government. But
nevertheless, that being said, there still was the truth that even within
the Roman government, a lot of tax collectors exceeded their license and
that would always be a problem, then you're no longer operating within
דינא דמלכותא דינא. Dina Demalchuta Dina. Okay, for one last thing I'll
say before we get to the next part, which is a very
juicy part which gets into a whole גזל גוי Gezel Goy question.
We will have to leave that for tomorrow, but let's just end,
I want to look at תוספות Tosafot נודע להרגין. Noda Lahargin. תוספות
Tosafot applies it to a practical case. תוספות Tosafot says in his
time, he says like this: He says, if you look at the
middle of the
תוספות, Tosafot, וכן נוהגים, Vechein Nohagim, about eight lines smack in the
middle of תוספות, Tosafot, starts with אחת אורגא. Achas Orega.
He says, וכן נוהגים כשהנסים מדירים היהודים הדרים תחתיהם שלא יצאו לדור
בעיר אחרת. Vechein nohagim k'shehanasim madirim hayehudim hadarim tachteichem shelo yeitsu ladur
b'ir acheres.
In the Middle Ages the big system question was about who had
a right to settle in different places, and they wanted to really
control in terms of the economics and so on. So Jews would
get a right to move to a new place to open up
new economic opportunities.
But the government would often
make people... there's the Pale of Settlement and all these things. You
would have to... it would be prohibited for you to leave a
certain region and they would make people take an oath that they
wouldn't leave, of course would limit the Jews' opportunity to make a
פרנסה. Parnassah. So they would make them take an oath. So he
says when they force them to take this oath, שלא יצאו לדור
בעיר אחרת, shelo yeitsu ladur b'ir acheres, יכולים לנדור סתם שלא יצאו.
yecholim lindor stam shelo yeitsu. Fine, I make a
נדר neder that I won't leave. And if I leave, like if
I take a שבועה shvua I won't leave or I make a
נדר neder that all stuff in the world will be אסור assur
to me. ובליבם יחשבו היום. Ubelibam yachshevu hayom. Okay, I swear I
won't leave and in my mind I think today. Okay. So it's
sort of just the exact context with this case. ואף על פי
שמפרש בשפתיו שלא יצא ממנו
כל ימי חייו. Ve'af al pi shemefaresh bisfasav shelo yeitsei mimenu kol
yemei chayav. Let's say they sort of catch on. They say, no,
take an oath that you'll never leave your entire life from this
region. Fine, I take an oath I'll never leave my entire life
from this region. יכול להרהר ולחשוב
בליבו שום תנאי. Yachol liharher velachshov belibo shum tenai. In your mind
you can say if I, whatever the if is, like if I
win the lottery tomorrow. If the sun doesn't rise tomorrow. Right. Okay.
ואם עיוות בשפתיו בלחש Ve'im ivata bisfasav belachash
and if you sort of were whispering in your undertone explicitly what
your condition was, כל שכן דהוי ביטול גמור kol sheken dahavei bitul
gamur then even better, you don't sort of say it out loud.
Sure, I promise I won't, whatever, and then you mumble something. But
anyway very interesting to see about the reality didn't change and about
the need that they had using taking an oath or a שבועה
shvua or a נדר neder in order to get them to abide
by it. Of course one does worry about the חילול השם Chillul
Hashem problem, after a while they start picking up on the fact
that the Jews are taking all these oaths and then they're going
ahead and doing it anyway, right?
Right, but you know what? Sometimes it was
also understood
that you have to placate your right wing. Right. So it's understood
that yeah, everything's above board here but everybody understands.
Oh, you mean even the person who's making you take the oath?
Oh, that could be. Alright, you mean like the government officer that's
making you do it. Oh, that could be. So we got through
this basic issue with דינא דמלכותא דינא Dina Demalchuta Dina and taking
money from people that have earned it through ill-gotten gains. Okay, very
juicy stuff. And tomorrow we pick up with a very important discussion
about גזל גוי. Gezel Goy. We're dealing with a משנה mishnah that
you
cannot directly exchange money from tax collectors, taking directly from the pouch
in which they have the tax money in because the assumption of
the משנה mishnah is that it is a type of גזל, Gezel,
which led to a very important discussion in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and
the גמרא, Gemara, that how could that be if דינא דמלכותא דינא?
Dina Demalchuta Dina? If the government has a right to do these
things. And it basically said that we're talking about a case where
they don't do it, either that they're not backed by the government
or they go outside the parameters that the government allows. And we
pointed out that this idea of דינא דמלכותא דינא Dina Demalchuta Dina
is specifically שמואל Shmuel from בבל. Bavel. שמואל Shmuel had a very
positive relationship with the government. בבל Bavel was a very welcoming society
and so on. And all the texts that see these things as
fundamentally illegitimate were coming from the תנאים Tanna'im and from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael where it was the oppressive Roman government and so on.
So that's a point that's made by scholars. But regardless, להלכה lehalacha
we adopt דינא דמלכותא דינא Dina Demalchuta Dina but said there are
cases in which somebody's operating outside of those parameters.
So that's the first set of answers, and that's why it's considered
to be גזל. Gezel. Now the גמרא Gemara however continues with a
new set of answers which raises a whole new fun topic, and
let's take a look. Right.
So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, seven lines from the bottom
on ק"ח עמוד א', kuf chet amud aleph,
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says: במוכס
כנעני. Bemoches Kena'ani. Now that is not the correct word, it's במוכס
גוי. Bemoches Goy. You know that a text is not... as I've
mentioned I think multiple times, the standard word in the גמרא Gemara
for a non-Jew is not עכו"ם, Akum, although that's what... see all
the time in the גמרא, Gemara, the standard word for the for
a non-Jew in the גמרא Gemara is either גוי Goy or נכרי,
Nochri, but because the sometimes the גמרא Gemara says things that are
disparaging and sometimes הלכות halachas that are
disfavorable towards non-Jews
and the when the church started finding out about this in the
Middle Ages because of apostates who told them about it, they would
start burning and censoring the תלמוד, Talmud, the Jews went through a
period of self-censorship
and changed all those references to גוי Goy to עכו"ם, Akum, which
means עובדי כוכבים ומזלות, ovdei kochavim umazalot, which means like a star
worshiper, so they could say it did not apply to the current
non-Jews. You know a גמרא Gemara is particularly problematic if it doesn't
even use the word עכו"ם Akum but it uses the word כנעני
Knani as a way of saying that this type of הלכה halacha
was never relevant, it only applied to these ancient Canaanite nations, has
nothing ever to do with anybody in the last three three millennia.
So anyway, the גמרא Gemara here that is going to start to
talk about a question about גזל כנעני, gezel Knani, stealing from a
גזל גוי, gezel Goy, stealing from a non-Jew, and that's how it
appears in the ראשונים Rishonim and in the manuscripts. In our גמרא
Gemara it consistently talks about גזל כנעני, gezel Knani, okay, a Canaanite,
but that's not the that's the edited version, okay, that's the PG
version. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so רב
אשי אמר Rav Ashi amar במוכס גוי bemochas Goy or כנעני, Knani,
we're talking about that the tax collector is a non-Jew. And therefore
what? Just because the government, what did the government say in the
case of tax collecting? The government said that, you know, we are
sort of said to be selling our tax giving the right to
collect taxes to this person because he paid us money to buy
that right to collect taxes, and therefore now everybody owes this person
the money. That's what the government said. Okay, so fine, so we
owe that person the money, but if he's a non-Jew and you're
allowed to steal from a non-Jew, which is the question,
then I didn't do an עבירה aveirah by stealing from him. Now
the I you know I didn't do anything wrong, it's allowed for
me to not pay the tax collector. Now the question is that's
a little strange because I mean we're going to get to the
non-Jew thing in a minute, but just to appreciate what we're also
saying about דינא דמלכותא, dina demalchuta, you would think the government rule
is also that you have to pay the guy. So who cares
if according to your laws you're allowed to, you know, whatever, not
pay non-Jews? The government rule is you have to pay, and whatever
happens to דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina demalchuta dina, you gotta follow the
government rules. So this גמרא Gemara actually makes it sound that דינא
דמלכותא דינא dina demalchuta dina does not mean that I have to
act in the ways that the government is dictating that I act.
Like just because it says that I have to not speed or
cross at the crosswalks, that's not דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina demalchuta dina.
That's telling me what to do and when I have to what
to do, I go by, you know, what the תורה Torah says.
Okay, what דינא דמלכותא דינא dina demalchuta dina is telling me is
that they determine essentially property rights. So therefore they can determine that
I owe money, you know, to pay taxes and that they have
a right to collect taxes, you know, and the right of eminent
domain, immanent domain or whatever, you know, eminent. Imminent. You know, they
can define it's sort of like it's sort of like, you know,
a type of a הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beis din hefker.
They can decide who owes who money, who has rights to property
and so on. Okay, but and therefore they say you, you know,
Christopher here brought the bought the right to collect taxes, he owns
that tax money and now you have to pay him. So דינא
דמלכותא דינא dina demalchuta dina says he owns the tax money, but
when they it's that they define property rights. Okay, whether or not
I have to pay him, that's a halachic question. That's not a
דינא דמלכותא דינא dina demalchuta dina question, right? So that actually is
what seems to emerge from this גמרא Gemara if you read it
closely because in the end of the day, who cares if he's
a non-Jew or not a non-Jew, wouldn't you just have to listen
to what the government says?
Meaning, just because he's a government official, you'd have to pay him.
But since he's some other guy that
bought no, even if he were a government official, all the government
if he seizes the property, then it's a legitimate act of taking
the property and then he legitimately owns it because the government decides
who owns money. But if he tells me that I have to,
I don't have to listen to the government I don't have to
follow government what the government is telling me to do.
The government just has a right to define property ownership. Okay, so
the government can build a wall but not make Mexico pay.
Well, you know, again, they can come and they can seize my
property, they can say I owe taxes, they can do all those
types of things, and I don't say it's גזל gezel because they
have a right to say who owns what. But they can't say
to me I have they they they can say to me I
have to pay because they're going to send the police in if
I don't, you know, they're entitled to do that, but if I
have a way and this is very unfortunate because you know
people will claim okay, you know, well you can cheat on your
taxes because alright, they say I owe money, but in the end
of the day if non-Jews and as we see in this discussion
you always have to pay your debts to non-Jews, הלכה halacha really
demands that, and just because the government says I do it, all
all the government can say is that I owe the money, whether
or not I have to pay it or not, like so, you
know, that you know that what this is?
That's what this is.
That's exactly what this is. So that is you know so there's
two sort of issues here. One is the scope of דינא דמלכותא
dina demalchuta and the other is this question about, you know, stealing
from non-Jews, which is what we're about to get to. Yes.
Okay, on good terms it's almost shifting it to like if I
gave No, the נפקא
מינא
*nafka mina* is, is that, well first of all the נפקא מינא
*nafka mina* is if גזל גוי gezel goy *gezel goy* is אסור
assur. *assur* then you do have to pay because you're stealing from
a non-Jew. The other נפקא מינא *nafka mina* is, is that if
they take money from you, Michael here and doesn't have to treat
that as stolen funds, because they had a right to take that
money. You didn't have an obligation to pay it, but they had
a right to take it. Okay, so then the somebody else doesn't
have to treat that as stolen funds.
I but what I'm not getting is the disconnect between your not
having to do it and they have a right to take it.
They went ahead and they seized your land and your field filled
with אתרוג *esrog* trees because you weren't paying off your back taxes.
Okay, now Michael goes and buys an אתרוג *esrog* from the government.
Can he use it on סוכות *Succos*? Is it an אתרוג הגזול
*esrog hagazul*? It's not an אתרוג הגזול *esrog hagazul*. They had a
right to say that you owed that money and they had a
right to seize it. Okay? But they but they can't make you
do something. Okay, they could with a police force, but they can't
הלכתית *halachically* make you. I mean they can make
a law, but they you know but like I don't have to
listen to it.
They can't exactly enforce it. I mean they can enforce it with
the police, but but I don't I don't have a religious דינא
דמלכותא דינא dina demalchuta dina, *Dina D'malchuta Dina* obligation to follow it.
Okay, that is what seems to be implicit in this statement of
רב אשי Rav Ashi *Rav Ashi*.
And is there a conceptual distinction that's going to be made aside
from you know between the government and an individual?
Well, that's the case of מכס העומד מאליו *mochas ha-omed me-eilav*. If
I'm just the local mafioso, then you're not obligated then then that
now what stage what defines a local government, you know, right, you
know, okay, that's a separate conversation, but if somebody is not a
recognized legal authority, you know, then it would not apply. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. You know, in some places whatever,
you know, tribal countries or whatever, you know, the local mafioso is
the legal political authority. So I'm serious, he is, you know, I
mean there's a lack of government control over the region. Like warlords.
Right, warlords, exactly.
I just meant I didn't mean that,
I just
meant your neighbor, Sam McGillicuddy. Yeah, what a guy. Yeah. About the
גזל גוי gezel goy *gezel goy* question, no. Okay, so let's go
back. Okay, so רב אשי אמר במכס גוי goy. כנעני Kena'ani *Rav
Ashi amar bemochas goy canani*, okay, and therefore it's not a problem
and therefore you don't you're not obligated to pay him and if
he takes it it's גזל gezel, *gezel*. דתניא *detanya* we taught a
ברייתא Braitah. *braita*, ישראל *Yisrael* again וגוי *vegoy* or
notice it's וכנעני אנס *ve-knani anas*, like a
violent Canaanite, okay, that's all an edited text, שבא לדין *sheba ledin*.
I mean originally it was ישראל
וגוי *Yisrael vegoy*.
No, it was just ישראל וגוי *Yisrael vegoy*. I think it's actually
ישראל ונוכרי *Yisrael venochri*. Okay.
And you didn't have the word אנס *anas* in there? Exactly.
שבא לדין *sheba ledin* that are coming for a court case. אם
אתה יכול לזכהו בדיני ישראל bedinei Yisrael *im atah yachol lezakao bedinei
Yisrael*, if you can judge according to Jewish law and make the
Jew win, זכהו *zakao*, then you judge by Jewish
law, ואמור לו כך דיננו *ve'emor lo kach dineinu* and you say,
look, this is our law, we're judging by our law, בדיני כנענים
*bedinei knanim* or נוכרים *nochrim* וזכהו ואמור לו כך דיניכם *vezakao ve'emor
lo kach dineichem*, or if you can make the Jew win applying
non-Jewish law, you apply non-Jewish law and you say, yeah, we're just
judging by your laws. Your, okay, ואם לאו *ve'im lav* and if
not, באין עליו בעקיפין *ba'in elav be'akifin*.
Then you find some devious scheme in order to make the Jew
win. So either you first of all there's always a question of
jurisdiction of which law to apply, so it's always going to be
in favor of the ישראל *Yisrael*. That is at least working within
some parameters of some legal parameters but obviously favor it's a favor
it's a favoritism type you know that's going on, selective favoritism. But
the third point the second point is that even if you can't
make him win by any legal system, you find some device in
order to help the Jew win. That's what רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael*
says. What does it mean? I don't know what it means. But
it means you work out whatever you know you you you scare
him you persuade him I don't you trick him. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva, אומר אין באין עליו בעקיפין *Rabbi Akiva omer ein ba'in elav
be'akifin*. No,
you do not do any types of deceptions or tricks מפני קידוש
השם Kiddush Hashem *mipnei kiddush hashem* because of a sanctification of God's
name which really also means like the reverse, if he finds out
what you've done, then it'll be a חילול השם Chillul Hashem. *chilul
hashem*. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ורבי עקיבא *ve-Rabbi Akiva* now רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva טעמיה קידוש השם kiddush Hashem. *Rabbi Akiva tamyei kiddush
hashem*. The only hesitation רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* has is the קידוש
השם kiddush Hashem *kiddush hashem* hesitation, and in circumstances maybe where that
wouldn't be a concern, he wouldn't be bothered. היכא דליכא קידוש השם
kiddush Hashem *heicha de-leka kiddush hashem*, if there would not be those
considerations, באין *ba'in*, then you could go ahead and use some device
and scheme etc. So you see that it is not a problem
of גזל גוי gezel goy *gezel goy* because here fundamentally the Jew
owes him the money and you're finding some way to prevent the
Jew from having to pay.
Would there ever be a circumstance where קידוש השם Hashem. *kiddush hashem*
is not at stake? Right, I mean, you and a גוי goy.
*goy* on an island.
Right, I mean, so that's always the question, right, exactly, right, yes,
if you're very מחמיר *machmir* on קידוש השם *kiddush hashem* hopefully that
closes the gaps, okay, but at least anyway in theory this is
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. גזל גוי gezel goy משרא *gezel
goy mishar*, one minute, you can't just say that it's permissible to
steal from a non-Jew. דתניא *detanya*, we taught a ברייתא *braita*, אמר
רבי שמעון דבר זה דרש רבי עקיבא *amar Rabbi Shimon davar ze
darash Rabbi Akiva* the same רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that until now
just made it a קידוש השם *kiddush hashem* point, he made the
following דרשה drasha *drasha*. כשבא מצפירים *keshe-ba mizafirin*, wherever צפירים *Zafirin* is,
מניין לגזל גוי goy. שהוא אסור she'hu assur, *minayin legezel goy she'hu
assur*?
How do you know it's forbidden to steal from a גוי goy,
*goy*? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar: אחרי נמכר גאולה תהיה לו *Talmud lomar
acharei nimkar geulah tihyeh lo*. This is about a Jew who sells
himself as a slave and then we have to redeem him, okay,
and one of the people he might sell himself as a slave
to is to a non-Jew.
Okay, so it says
גאולה *geulah* redemption שלא ימשכנו ויצא *she-lo yimshechenu ve-yeitzei* that you should
not just forcibly snatch him and he goes out. maybe you should,
you know,
maybe you should go ahead and basically try to the way תוספות
Tosafos reads this, deceive the non-Jew, persuade him, pressure him, try to
free the Jew in less than fully above board ways. What is
the word יגלום? yiglum? I don't know. תלמוד לומר: ושיב עם קונהו.
veshiv im koneihu. וחישב עם קונהו, vekishav im koneihu, excuse me.
You shall, you know, you should do
the, you know, you should do the
books with the purchaser. ידקדק עם קונהו. yedakdek im koneihu.
You have to be very מדקדק, medakdek, you know, you have to
be very above board and buy him back at his true value
from the non-Jew. So even though there's a מצוה mitzvah here to
be פודה podeh a Jew who's a slave in a non-Jewish home,
nevertheless you cannot use any deception or whatever, you can't steal him
away. So you see, גזל גוי אסור. gezel goy assur. אמר רב
יוסף לא קשיא. Amar Rav Yosef lo kashya. So how do you
reconcile these two רבי עקיבא, you know, or this statement with what
has been claimed about the case of the tax collector? It's not
difficult. הא בתנאי הא בגירתוש, Ha bitznani ha bigirtosh, really, הא בגוי
הא בגר תושב. ha be-goy ha be-ger toshav.
When is it that it's forbidden, it's permissible by a standard non-Jew.
When is it
forbidden, when it's a גר תושב, ger toshav, somebody who actually is,
you know, observes the seven נח Noach laws, lives among us like
a more
law-abiding, you know, type of a non-Jew.
So this is to say then, you know, it really... Right, correct.
But the גמרא Gemara is not going to keep with that. I
mean, it's always a good point in general what Michael says, but
let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers then I'll get back to
that. So אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said to
him, והא תרוייהו גבי הדדי כתיבי. veha tarvaihu gabei adadi ketivei. Wait
a minute, this פסוק pasuk that we're learning about redeeming the Jew
is, in those פסוקים psukim it talks both about a גר תושב
ger toshav and about a standard גוי. goy, Okay, כתיבי: ketivei: לא
לך אלא גר, lo lecha ela ger, because in a דרשה that
says like, you know, if because you're going to like deal incorrectly
with money of שביעית, shvi'is, of שמיטה, shmita, because all this is
in the פרשה parsha of שמיטה, shmita, you'll wind up having to
sell yourself, and you won't sell yourself just to a fellow Jew,
you'll have to sell yourself to a גר תושב, ger toshav, שנאמר
לגר. shene'emar lager. It says and you'll sell to a גר. ger.
ולא לגר צדק, velo le-ger tzedek, not only to a righteous convert,
אלא גר תושב, ela ger toshav, but even a non-Jew, a גר
תושב. ger toshav. שנאמר לגר תושב. shene'emar leger toshav. Okay, and then
it goes on to say משפחת גר. mishpachat ger. So what does
משפחת גר mishpachat ger come to include? זהו עכו"ם, zeu akum, that's
even a full non-Jew, not even a גר תושב ger toshav you're
selling yourself. כשהוא אומר, keshehu omer, and then it goes and the
verse continues and says או לעקר משפחת גר, o le-eker mishpachat ger,
or to an עקר, eker, whatever that means, but here what we're
tripping is זהו נמכר לעבודת כוכבים. zeu nimkar le'avodat kochavim. You not
only sell yourself to a non-Jewish family, you're selling yourself to a
pagan temple. You're now going to be working in the wood chopper
for a pagan temple. Even like for עקר, eker, you have to
עוקר? oker? I guess so, I don't know. Anyway, so we're reading
this פסוק pasuk that you can sell yourself to the most offensive,
you know, theologically offensive type of a context, and nevertheless we can't
come and steal you away. We have to actually legitimately buy your
freedom. Okay, so you see that גזל גוי אסור. gezel goy assur.
אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, so how are we going to
reconcile it? רבא Rava says, obviously it's a מחלוקת, machlokes, but if
we want to reconcile, well it's funded by רבי עקיבא in both
places. So רבא Rava says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult.
כאן בגזל כאן בהפקעת הלוואתו. kan begezel kan be-hafkakat halvato. And this
is actually how it's פסק paskened להלכה. lehalacha. Stealing is אסור. asur.
Actually actively taking something out of somebody's control and taking it to
mine. If it's already, right, right, right, if it's money that's owed
and I'm not paying money that's owed, I'm not actively stealing something
away, I'm just passively not paying up my debts, that's permissible. So
how does that explain the evidence? So taxes is not paying my
debt. That's why if it's a non-Jew, it's considered I can go
ahead, it's considered, now it's still a little bit funny, because A,
it's one thing to say I don't have to pay my debt.
I want to point out that it's even more deeply problematic because
we're saying the idea that it was a non-Jewish tax collector to
explain why it was considered to be גזל, gezel. why the money
in this pouch was considered to be גזל. gezel. It's one thing
to say, alright, it's only paying a debt, you're allowed to not
do that. Okay, but now we're saying if I actually did pay
the debt, or if he seized the money, it's considered גזל. gezel.
It still doesn't explain why it's considered גזל. gezel? Right, remember this
answer is explaining if דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina demalchusa dina why is
the money of the tax collector גזל? gezel. So saying that I
don't have an obligation to pay it does not explain why when
I do pay it or when he does take it, it is
גזל. gezel? So that's anyway just question number one. But the tax
question is a case of הפקעת הלוואתו. hafkakat halvato. The question about
when they're coming to the court case and we basically try to
persuade the non-Jew or trick the non-Jew to say that the Jew
doesn't owe him money, that's also הפקעת הלוואתו, hafkakat halvato, that's a
passive not paying, that's allowed. But when it comes to taking the
Jew out of the non-Jewish household, right, taking the slave, the Jewish
slave out of the non-Jewish house, that's stealing something from the non-Jew,
that's not allowed. Now the גמרא Gemara makes one more point about
this and then I want to go back to something. אמר ליה
אביי עבד נמי הפקעת הלוואתו הוא. Amar lei Abaye eved nami hafkakat
halvato hu. No, a Jewish slave is not that the
non-Jew owns the body of the Jew.
It's that the Jew is somehow like working off a debt. He
owes service to the non-Jew. So if he were to steal away,
if he were to steal away, he wouldn't be giving the non-Jew
the service he owes him, but he wouldn't be stealing anything. He's
not owned by the non-Jew. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, רבא
לטעמיה, Rava leta'ameih, no, רבא Rava disagrees with that. רבא Rava goes
according to his reasoning, דאמר רבא, de'amar Rava, עבד עברי גופו קנוי.
eved ivri gufo kanuy. No, there is a way in which an
עבד עברי, eved ivri, it's not owned to the same degree as
a non-Jewish slave, but maybe it's an ownership למעשה ידיו. lema'aseh yadav.
But if I, if somebody is my non-Jew, my Jewish slave, I
actually have property rights in that person. So if you were, if
I was the non-Jew and you were to steal my Jewish slave
away from me, you would not just be preventing me from getting
the labor that I'm entitled to, you would be stealing away from
me something in which I have property rights. That would be גזל
גוי gezel goy, and that would be אסור. asur, So this actually
winds up to be ההלכה, ha-halacha, that גזל גוי gezel goy is
אסור, assur. הפקעת הלוואתו hafkas halva'aso is מותר. mutar. You combine it
with the earlier discussion about the scope of דינא דמלכותא דינא Dina
d'malchuta dina. and you get obviously very disturbing claims relating to things
like paying taxes and whatnot. So whatever, that's obviously a whole שיעור
shiur in itself. Either way it's disturbing, even if it was about
a more bigger thing about paying, even if it was just about
not paying somebody money you owe them. Now Michael does say correctly
that the גמרא Gemara doesn't sort of, this is within גזל גוי
gezel goy there are these distinctions. It seems like that if somebody
really was a גר תושב, ger toshav, that the גמרא Gemara is
not rejecting what it said before. Like none of this is true
by גר תושב, ger toshav, גר תושב ger toshav you're not allowed
to do any of this stuff. So it is, you could come
and say that nowadays and there are those that say something along
these lines, like everybody who's law-abiding citizens and so on, the general
presumption that people basically, not everybody, but the basic presumption, that's what
society expects of people and those are the norms of society, like
everybody at least for these types of monetary הלכות halachos has a
status of a גר תושב, ger toshav, which would basically and there
are definitely פוסקים, poskim, not only contemporary 21st century פוסקים, poskim, throughout
the years that have basically tried to do away with these types
of distinctions and claim that we live with God-fearing non-Jews or law-abiding
non-Jews and so on, and these types of distinctions were only present
in societies in which non-Jews would be grabbing every opportunity to take
advantage of Jews. Right. Right. Now, by the way, now sometimes they're
saying it because of censors. Sometimes they're saying it because they really
believe it. Like if you look at the bottom at the footnote,
there's a little א aleph in רש״י, Rashi, א aleph in a
half parenthesis. Okay, look what it says: לפי שנהגו—now kefi she-nahagu obviously
the reason they're printing this in the גמרא Gemara is not just
to teach you הלכה. halacha. It never tells us הלכה halacha otherwise,
nobody does ever glossing, that would be what Michael would want, somebody
that constantly gloss and tell us what the הלכה למעשה halacha lema'aseh
is. The reason it's telling it to you here is because obviously
this is a very deeply disturbing issue and it's to deal with
the type of a dealing with the reality of how are the
non-Jews around us going to deal with this if they read this.
So if you look at the footnote or what are we going
to think about it, anyway, לפי שנהגו ככנענים—again kefi she-nahagu ke-kena'anim ככנענים,
ke-kena'anim, מנהג הפקר בממונא דאחריני. minhag hefker bemamona de'achrinei. Okay, because they
treat other people's property as they don't respect other people's property and
they לכן מדדו להם מדותם ודנום כדיניהם. lachein modedu lahem midusam vedanum
kedineihem. That's why the חז״ל Chazal felt that it was legitimate to
at least do הפקעת הלוואה. hafka'as halva'ah. Okay. So, and if you
similarly see, if you look at the next one, לפי שנצמדו הכותים
בבא—we kefi shenitzmedu hakusim bebava didn't get up there yet, but whatever—לילידי
ז' אומות למנהגיהם liyaledi zayin umos leminhageihem ולכן דינם בדיני ממונות כדין
ז' אומות. ulachen dinam bedinei mamonus kedin zayin umos. Or so it
gives both reasons. Either they were real pagans and they didn't, were
not basically sort of like God-fearing people or they were real like
pagans, or they also were people that didn't respect property. So there
are these things, sometimes they're said because of the censor, sometimes they're
said because genuinely the פוסקים poskim feel that how can you live
with such these unjust types of laws and laws also that encourage
terrible types of acts, moral acts among Jews. So that's to understand,
to put this in some type of a historical context and to
see that it's no longer sort of relevant nowadays. But what remains
deeply disturbing is that people who are looking for a basis for
cheating and not being honest in monetary matters, especially when dealing with
non-Jews, can base themselves on גמרות Gemaros like these. Interestingly, just thinking
about this contemporarily, there have been so many people, the latest housing
crisis, just walked away from their mortgages, right? Those are non-Jews, not
just everybody. It's the same thing, like, I don't pay them. Right,
although there there's property to be seized or whatever, but right and
there the... I understand. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Alright,
we're going to go on with this topic. Okay, so, now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רב ביבי בר גידל אמר רב
שמעון חסידא, Amar Rav Bibi bar Gidel amar Rav Shimon Chasida, גזל
גוי אסור. gezel goy asur. So now we have it said. directly
stealing is forbidden, אבדתו מותרת, Aveidato mutares, not returning his lost object
is permissible. That's sort of like הפקעת הלוואתו, hafka'as halvah'so, you're just
passively not giving. You know, one could say that it's even makes
more sense, you know, since when do I have to return lost
objects? Is that necessarily obviously true that there I should be obligated
to return somebody's lost object? On the other, you know, it's maybe
it's even less of an obligation than if I borrowed money. I
borrowed money, I really that creates an obligation to pay back. On
the other hand, here it is a concrete physical object. It's not
like an abstract debt. It's not like I owe you $100. There's
a concrete object in my house that's yours that I'm not giving
to you. I found your iPhone, I'm not giving it to you.
Okay, assuming that you don't know that I have it, because otherwise
it's a חילול השם. Chillul Hashem, So wouldn't that also imply that
the thing above then? Like about the גזל כנעני? Gezel Kena'ani? Yeah,
we said that it's אסור. assur No, no, no, but even the
גזל כנעני Gezel Kena'ani when you talk about all that, but like
if it's חילול השם, Chillul Hashem if they're going to find... חילול
השם Chillul Hashem is the is going to be revisited. Anytime there's
a חילול השם Chillul Hashem, issue. Of course you really just want
to say to somebody, yeah, it's אסור assur to steal on your
taxes because you'll get found out and then there'll be חילול השם,
Chillul Hashem. the only reason is חילול השם. Chillul Hashem But it
is true, you know, if you take חילול השם Chillul Hashem. seriously,
hopefully that prevents you from doing 99% of these things. Okay. Yes,
but again, isn't that like saying if I get caught? You're saying
if he finds out... Well, what you say is it's אסור assur,
for you to do it because you might get caught. But then
somebody will say, no, I'm really good at doing this, I'm not
going to get caught, I don't have to be concerned about חילול
השם. Chillul Hashem. You know, then we can debate how much likely
does it have to be that I'm going to get caught that
I should be concerned about the possible חילול השם. Chillul Hashem And
it goes to your relationship with השם. Well, okay, so some who
want to bring, you know, who want to obviously address all these
ethically and problem all these ethical problems want to reframe קידוש השם
and saying, it's not just what other people will perceive. Something that
leads to a חילול השם Chillul Hashem. is obviously something that is
intrinsically morally problematic. It's not just that oh, those גוים Goyim have
weird ideas that you're supposed to pay your debts and it's going
to be a חילול השם. Chillul Hashem, Like if people think that
this is a desecration of the divine name, then that means that
there's something inherently problematic with this act. Okay, but I'm not sure
that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying, but that definitely is a
desire that some people have to read in the גמרא Gemara like
this. I see, I see. I was going to also build on
something similar. Like חילול השם, Chillul Hashem, it's not just I might
get caught and punished. I don't have a responsibility to the reputation
of... No, that is what it means. It's not punishment. It's that
I'll get caught and then people will know that this פרום frum
Jew was stealing his on his taxes. Exactly, that is what it
means. That is what it means. Yeah, it's not the punishment but
but if I never get caught, there's no חילול השם, Chillul Hashem.
you know? So then we can debate, oh well, I think I
won't get caught, so I'm not concerned about חילול השם. Chillul Hashem
I know that I'm not going to get caught. But yes, the
point is is that taking חילול השם Chillul Hashem, to the next
logical step is there's a reason why it's a חילול השם, chillul
Hashem you know? So, okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: Okay, the not only so is הפקעת הלוואתו מותר, hafka'as halvah'so
mutar, you don't have to return his lost object. דאמר רב הונא
מניין לגזל גוי, De'amar Rav Huna minayin le'gezel goy, again repeating a
שיטה, shita, שהוא אסור, assur. שנאמר, shenemar, ואכלת את כל העמים אשר
ה׳ אלקיך נתן לך. v'achalta es kol ha'amim asher Hashem Elokecha nosein
lach. You shall consume all the nations that God gives you בזמן
שהם מסורים בידך, bezman she'heim mesurim beyadecha, when they're given over to
you like when you've conquered them in war, then that's when you
have some right to seize their property. Okay, ולא בזמן שאינם מסורים
בידך. v'lo bezman she'einam mesurim beyadecha. Okay, but if they're not, now
maybe that also reflects a reality like not just we're not conquering
them in war, but also reflects a reality like uh, we're living
in גלות, Galus, you know? We're living under, you know, their rule.
Uh, we gotta sort of incorporate that that reality into our into
our lives. Anyway, so anyway, but you're not allowed to steal. אבדתו
מותרת. Aveidato mutares. דאמר רב חמא בר גוריא אמר רב מניין לאבידת
גוי שהוא מותרת, De'amar Rav Chama bar Gurya amar Rav minayin l'aveidas
goy she'hu mutares, how do you know it's permissible not to return
their lost object? שנאמר לכל אבידת אחיך, Shenemar lechol aveidas achicha, to
all of lost objects of your brother. לאחיך אתה מחזיר ואי אתה
מחזיר לגוי. L'achicha atah machzir v'ee atah machzir l'goy. Okay, you do
it to your brother but not to a non-Jew. If you look
again at the side, שנוהגים shenohagim the little margin on the left,
שנוהגים הפקר בקנייני אחרים. shenohagim hefker bekinyanei acheirim. All these glosses, right,
because anybody reading this is aware about how problematic these statements is.
But הפקר? hefker? One minute, I'm going to and if you look
at the gloss on the right, you have a similar point: שיש
להם בלאו כמוך נימוסים ומשפטים צדיקים בדברים שבין אדם לחברו. sheyesh lahem
belav kamocha nimusim umishpatim tzadikim bidevarim shebein adam lachaveiro. They will if
they are your אחיך achicha not because they're your fellow Jew, they're
your אחיך achicha because they have a just legal system that respects
property, then you are חייב chayiv to return lost objects. So then
it is a גר תושב? Ger Toshav? גר תושב, Ger Toshav, right.
Anyway, so there's a constant glossing going on here, right, both I
think because of the obvious moral issues and also possibly just because
of a concern about how some outsider going to read this text.
Yeah, I had that because it was going to be answered, but
what's my problem here is both the both the Persian Zoroastrian society
and the Romans, pagans had very serious legal systems. It wasn't like
a הפקר hefker or barbarians. Right, so there's two answers, that's a
good question. Number one is with the Romans, I don't know enough
about this, but clearly they you know there was all the Hadrianic
persecutions and so on. They might have had a legal system and
but that might have been side by side with persecuting and exploiting
the Jews, so... that's to perceive how just the whole system is
is one thing. But the other point is is that you know
I think there's a little bit of a historical fiction going on
here meaning when we try to put these גמרות Gemarot in a
historical context is it the right the real historical context or is
it a claimed historical context in order to somehow limit the scope
of what's being said. Now but I actually do believe that whether
or not the legal system was just I actually do believe that
a lot of these הלכות Halachot emerged from a thousands of years
or you know or hundreds of years of hostile violent non-Jewish you
know dominion over Jews. And that leads to a certain sense about
like you know like Czarist Russia whatever you can steal away from
the Czar and save for yourself is a מצוה Mitzvah you know
because that's the reality of this hostile government it leads to a
very different type of a perception you know. So I mentioned the
other day you know רב משה Rav Moshe basically writes a תשובה
Teshuvah and said of course you can't like like like cheat on
the regents or like you know apply for government grants that you
don't deserve misrepresent yourself he says this is a מדינה של חסד
Medina Shel Chessed this is not Czarist Russia you know this is
a government that cares about its citizens and protects its citizens. So
you know it that very powerfully colors you know your whole perspective
on these things. Yes. I found that interesting about the אחיך דהיינו
כמוך achicha d'hainu kamocha and יהודים משפטי צדיקים Yehudim mishpatei tzaddikim which
I think is צדיקים tzaddikim but sometimes it's אהבת המצוות ahavat hamitzvot
you know. No no no that's clearly not what the פשט pshat
of the גמרא Gemara means. That's a it's like a מאירי Meiri
read of the גמרא Gemara but it's being claimed in the gloss
as a way of toning down what's being said. Okay the גמרא
Gemara means Jew. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אבדת עובד כוכבים
מותרת. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav avadat oved kochavim muteret. ואימא הני
מילי היכא דלא אתא לידיה v'eima hanei milei heicha d'lo ata lidei
that means you don't have to pick it up and return it.
You can leave it on the ground. Okay דלא מיחייב לאהדורי בתרה.
d'lo mechayev l'ahadorei batrah. You don't have to run after him. אבל
היכא דאתא לידיה Aval heicha d'ata lidei once you already picked it
up, אימא ליהדרה eima lihadra then maybe you're holding onto his object
maybe you have to give it back? אמר רבינא ומוצאתה דאתא לידיה
משמע. Amar Ravina u'metza'atah d'ata lidei mashma. No it says וכל אבדת
אחיך אשר תאבד ממנו ומצאתה. v'chol avedat achicha asher tovad mimenu u'metza'atah.
Anybody's anything your brother loses that he loses and you find. So
it sounds like you found it, you picked it up and nevertheless
if it's not your brother's you don't have to return it. תניא
Tanya we learned in a ברייתא. רבי פנחס בן יאיר אומר. Rabbi
Pinchas ben Yair omer. במקום שיש חילול השם B'makom sheyesh chillul Hashem
now we're going to make a stronger statement about that if there
is חילול השם chillul Hashem which presumably means if there's even a
concern of חילול השם chillul Hashem. but again that's always a question
how do you define what the scope is. אפילו אבדתו אסור Afilu
avadato assur then you have to even return the lost you can't
even keep a lost object to yourself. And presumably same about הפקעת
הלוואתו. hafka'at halva'ato. Okay? אמר שמואל טעותו מותרת. Amar Shmuel ta'uto muteret.
If however let's say they make a mistake okay they accidentally you're
in a business deal and they didn't catch a point or you're
at the supermarket and they give you extra change okay you don't
have to return it. That's even better than הפקעת הלוואתו. hafka'at halva'ato.
Okay you're not like actively having incurred a debt and now you're
actively denying it. You're just not pointing out to them like a
mistake that they made. I mean you give every... Rabbi Pinchas ben
Yair says חילול השם. chillul Hashem No we're going to see that
every claim here has to accommodate the חילול השם chillul Hashem concern.
Okay? So in a case where you can accommodate the חילול השם
chillul Hashem. and that's maybe why he says טעותו. ta'uto. He's not
even aware that he made a mistake. So it won't be a
חילול השם. chillul Hashem Now maybe he's testing you. Maybe he'll find
out he made a mistake. So we're going to actually see cases
like that in a minute. I have to tell you the flip
of the חילול השם chillul Hashem is the קידוש השם. The biggest
the biggest and the least expensive קידוש השם ever which happens multiple
times in my life is somebody gives you change at the supermarket
and they gave you like an extra dollar or an extra twenty
cents and you know actually you gave me extra and here it's
back. Like people are shocked out of their mind. Like who the
heck you know points out that they got extra money and returns
it? Okay so anyway but here is the point about if they
make a mistake in your favor like it's Monopoly you know it's
always funny Monopoly what is that like bank error in your favor
collect fifty dollars. Yeah if they ever find out you're giving back
those fifty dollars. Okay so anyway this is saying you're allowed to
keep it okay but of course there's still going to be a
קידוש השם problem חילול השם chillul Hashem problem so let's take a
look. כי הא דשמואל Ki ha d'Shmuel like שמואל Shmuel זבן zavan
again מכותי mi'Kuti or מגוי mi'goi לקנא דדהבא likna d'dahava he bought
a Rashi says it's like a sensor like a fire pan of
gold במר דפרזלא b'mar d'parzla but the non-Jew thought it was copper.
So he bought it at the price for copper בד' זוזי b'dalet
zuzai for four zuz. So Rashi says what that it's very cheap
and not only that ועיבר ליה חד זוזא v'eibur leh chad zuza
and as if that weren't enough he really only paid him three
zuz for the four zuz price because the non-Jew wasn't counting the
money. Okay so... that's what it means? Yeah that's where that's what
Rashi says it means. I don't know it's it's vague. Reference... he
added... he added an extra zuz? Yeah what they said over there
is he added one so as to think oh he made a
mistake in the counting so he also made a mistake that it
was really a bronze one so he would like he did it
to like as an even greater הערמה. ha'aramah. So it's like oh
he wasn't being careful at all he didn't notice it was gold
he didn't notice you know he overpaid so that way he sort
of masked the fact. Wait but שמואל Shmuel but I don't understand
שמואל Shmuel is buying he's buying a gold one under the presumption...
so שמואל Shmuel is... He's the one paying. He only paid and
you know he's paying the going rate for a bronze one, which
is. That's what I just said. No, but then he added a
fifth. Right. So it's like the guy would think that he overpaid.
That he overpaid for that and not even be thinking, oh, I
got the better deal, so it minimizes the chances of it even
being. That's weird. That's not what רש"י Rashi says. He says תוס'
חריש שעיכב זוז מדמיו. Tos' Charish she-ikeiv zuz midamav. He paid in
חשבון cheshbon that he took three במקום bimkom four. No, רש"י Rashi
says he underpaid. All right, fine. Anyway, whatever. Moving on. Okay. אמר
ליה, amar lei, anyway שמואל Shmuel says to him, add insult to
injury. Exactly. So שמואל Shmuel then said to him though, חזי דלא
חסמינא. chazi dela chasmina. So שמואל Shmuel said look, what do I
know, I don't know gold, copper, the value of this metal, whatever,
I'm not counting the money, you count, I'm trusting you regarding everything.
So because he explicitly said he's trusting him, right, then it means
that even if he finds out that he was cheated, you know,
it won't be a חילול השם chillul Hashem because well, like he
said he didn't know, he was trusting me, clearly, you know, I
should have checked, he was telling me that he was trusting me
about it. So that's his way of protecting himself from a possible
חילול השם chillul Hashem that could emerge. What about רב כהנא? Rav
Kahana? Where's רב כהנא? Rav Kahana? We're not up to that. Oh,
I'm sorry, I skipped a line. I skipped a line. Thank you.
I skipped a line. Right, that was the end of שמואל Shmuel's
case. I skipped a line. רב כהנא Rav Kahana זבן מכותי מאה
ועשרין חביתא במאה. zavan mikutsi mea ve-esrim chavita bemea. So he bought
120 barrels, you know, at the price of 100. ויהב ליה חד
זוזא. ve-yav lei chad zuza. And somehow also he got it at
too low of a price and he even paid less, or the
way you're saying he paid a little more so the guy was
distracted. Whatever it was. אמר ליה, amar lei, okay, and here he
says חזי דלא חסמינא. chazi dela chasmina. Look, I don't know, I'm
not counting, I'm not paying so close attention, I'm trusting you. Okay,
and that way because he said I'm trusting you, it protected him
from a possible חילול השם chillul Hashem type of a concern. Okay.
But if he's doing that, that you know he's paying less and
he's actively, you know, notes it's טעות. taut. No, he's paying a
little less, and he's doing that, right? He knows he messed up.
You're saying why is that גזל? gezel? So טעות, taut, it's not
the same. No, I'm not paying close attention, I'm just giving him,
that's it. Yeah, that's what the גמרא Gemara seems to be. That's
a type of הפקעת הלוואתו. hafka'at halva'ato. I'm not actively sticking my
hand in his pocket and taking money out of his pocket, I'm
just not giving him everything he deserves. It's a type of like
הפקעת הלוואתו. hafka'at halva'ato. But you're right, it's not the same degree
of טעות taut so that he handed over the money to me
and I don't have to hand it back. Right, you give him
too much. Right, I understand. I took a gold thing from him
at a very cheap price. That's obviously a little bit of a
different, you know, they anyway they have those stories, right, that some
people go some somebody goes I mean there was a recent story
about this in the newspaper a year or two ago, you know,
somebody went to like some garage sale or whatever it is, you
know, and somebody was selling these like you know every time you
go some you know to one of these like caves they sell
you these like you know these colored stones like you get a
whole bucket of them for like two dollars or five dollars. Anyway,
so somebody was selling that and somebody was like looking through and
he saw something that actually was like a precious stone, it actually
was like some you know emerald or whatever, you know, and he
bought it for like a dollar or something like that, you know.
And then there's these other and I bought a מגילה Megilla from
a non-Jew on the street for $20. Really? Interesting. Is that גזל?
gezel Well, I don't know. Question is also did he have it
how did he have it? You know, but that's that might be
a מצוי מידם matzui mi-yadam type of an issue. You know, then
there was this other story I remember in the New York Times
a few years ago about this פרום frum Jew that bought a
like a desk or whatever from somebody and then you know he
pulled aside the panel and he found like whatever a hundred thousand
dollars and he returned it to the person, you know. So anyway,
but yeah, so all of those are sort of things about with
you know anything short of putting your hand in the guy's pocket
seems to sort of be in this טעות taut הפקעת הלוואתו hafka'at
halva'ato type of case. Okay. But but if he's doing that, then
you know, he's paying less and he's actively, you know, he's saying
though you can get around it and there won't be a חילול
השם chillul Hashem. and they're totally okay. Right. So is this it's
not ועשית הישר והטוב בעיני השם. va-asita ha-yashar ve-ha-tov be-einei Hashem. I
mean, that's what I said. That's why you have all those glosses
on the side that are trying to close that gap because it
is deeply disturbing from some ethical, you know, perspective. But then how
is it what we were seeing before about the the whole tax,
I thought we went past this and then no, it's all consistent.
גזל גוי gezel goy. is אסור, הפקעת הלוואתו hafka'at halva'ato is מותר
mutar as long as you avoid חילול השם. Chillul Hashem, Okay. So
it's just more of the same thing. Exactly. Variation, I mean whatever,
illustrating it, nuancing it, but it's all the same. Okay. רבינא Ravina
זבן דקלא. zavan dikla. I remember growing up that there was like
a story I think in the Jewish press, you know, they had
like these I don't know Tales of Sages all all these whatever.
Anyway, it somehow it stuck in my head. They had this one
story about some case where the Tsar or whatever it was, you
know, demands from the Jew like taxes or whatever, some unfair thing,
right, and he has him like you know he has to give
him like you know a field of like you know a hundred
yards by a hundred yards of grain, right? So the guy says
like he says look, I don't have it all together, like let's
could I give it in installments? So now I'll give 50 by
50 and then a month from now I'll give another 50 by
50. So that was just half of 100 by 100, right? Because
it's 100 by 50. Anyway, so this was like showing how brilliant
the Jew was, how he managed. Anyway, so it's a little. Anyway,
so it's a little, you know, whatever. I mean if the government
is the Czar's government stealing your grain, okay, wonderful. If it's a
real debt that you owe, you know, that raises these like moral
problems. Okay, anyway. רבינא זבן דיקלא, Ravina zvin dikla, רבינא Ravina bought
a palm tree. הוא וכותי ושותפא, Hu v'Kuti v'shutfa, he and a
כותי Kuti were partners in the palm tree. Okay, Samaritan, whatever. אמר
ליה לשמעיה, Amar lei l'Shamaei, he said this actually might be כותי
Kuti actually. What does שטיינזלץ Steinzaltz have? Does anybody have שטיינזלץ? Steinzaltz?
No. This actually might be כותי Kuti because we switched from כנעני
Kena'ani to כותי. Kuti. I have to check it. כותי Kuti here
also in the ArtScroll. Yeah, but I don't, what did the ArtScroll
say before? It said כנעני Kena'ani before, right? Right. Yeah, no, so
I want to know what the actual original text was. Okay, anyway,
הוא וכותי. Hu v'Kuti. Anyway, so he said to his attendant, קדים
ואייתי מעיקרא. Kadem v'aisi mi'ikara. צלחא. Tzalcha. צלחא Tzalcha means attendant? No,
צלחא Tzalcha means to chop up for firewood. Okay, he said to
his attendant, קדים ואייתי מעיקרא. Kadem v'aisi mi'ikara. Go and get my
half of the tree from the base of the tree, which is
obviously much thicker than the top of the tree. Okay. כותי מניינא
ידעי Kuti minyana yada because the Samaritan, if that's the right גירסא,
gersa, he only knows numbers, he knows quantity, not quality. That's not
גזל gezel, then. Meaning, that's just like being smart in business, right?
Meaning, no, isn't it? We both agreed, we agreed we're going to
pay for the tree equally and split it. And my idea of
splitting it is I get the bottom half, which is eighty percent
of the wood, okay? Meaning, like he wants the, no, he knows
that you got, you know, you got ten logs and I got
ten logs. The fact that my ten logs were three times as
big as his ten logs, he doesn't pay attention to that. Alright.
Alright, רב אשי הוה קאזיל באורחא. Rav Ashi havay ka'aze b'orcha. רב
אשי was going on the way. וחזא שיבשא דגופנא בפרדיסא. V'chaza shivsha
d'gufna b'pardesa. He saw a branch of a vine in the garden.
ותלי ביה חיתופא דענבי V'tali beh chitupha d'anvei and there was a
cluster of grapes. אמר ליה לשמעיה, Amar lei l'Shamaei, he said to
his attendant, זיל חזי, Zil chazi, go check that out. אי דכותי
נינהו אייתי, I d'Kuti ninhu aisi, if they belong to again Samaritan,
I want to check, I just have to stop to check what
the שטיינזלץ Steinzaltz גירסא gersa was this really is כותי. Kuti. Meaning
also maintenance, you know, that there's חילול השם, this wouldn't be allowed.
Right. And those who maintain that this רישא reisha doesn't apply, this
is just, no, no, no, it's all גוי. goy, It's not כותי,
Kuti, גוי גוי גוי, goy goy goy, it's all גוי. goy, Okay,
okay, okay. So go and see, I why'd it switch from כנעני
to כותי? Kuti? Maybe because this is a little less offensive, I
don't know. It's a fascinating question. Anyway, okay. זיל חזי אי דגוי
נינהו אייתי, Zil chazi i d'goy ninhu aisi, if it's a non-Jew,
if it's a non-Jew's take the cluster. אי דישראל נינהו לא תייתי,
I d'Yisrael ninhu lo taisi, if it's a Jew's not. Now that
seems like a straight case of גזל גוי, gezel goy. right? You're
just stealing the grapes off the vine. So איהו הוה גוי, Ihu
havay goy, so a certain non-Jew who was like there by the
road heard, דהוה יתיב בפרדיסא, d'havay yatib b'pardesa, he was sitting in
the garden and he heard what this exchange. אמר ליה Amar lei
and he said, דגוי שרי? d'goy shari? What? You're allowed to steal
from a גוי, just take the grapes? אמר ליה, Amar lei, no,
no, no. גוי שקיל דמי. Goy shakal damei. No, if it was
a גוי, he'd be okay with me taking it, I'm planning on
paying. If it's a Jew, I have to ask for permission before
I take. So if it was a גוי, I know he'd be
okay, they tend to be okay as long as you pay them
in the end. You know גוי, and all they care about is
money. Okay, but ישראל לא שקיל דמי, Yisrael lo shakal damei, but
if it's a Jew, he would not agree to it. I can't
take it on the assumption that he'd be okay with me paying.
Now תוספות Tosafos says, was this just an excuse or did he
really mean it? So תוספות Tosafos says, the whole dominant position of
this גמרא Gemara. is גזל gezel גוי is אסור. And if he
held that גזל gezel. גוי was מותר, mutar, then the גמרא Gemara
would have made that more clear. Right, the גמרא Gemara here has
completely consistent there. So תוספות Tosafos assumes that he really did was
serious about this. He really did mean it. He meant to take
it and to pay back. But nevertheless, right, exactly. That's at least
what תוספות says. Of course then, you know, you could say then
what's it doing in this discussion? Alright, anyway. גופא אמר שמואל. Gufa
amar Shmuel. Now that was a nice fun and very weighty and
whatever challenging discussion about גזל gezel, גוי. Now we're going to go
back to דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina d'malchuta dina, Okay, גופא אמר שמואל
דינא דמלכותא דינא, Gufa amar Shmuel dina d'malchuta dina, the law of
the government is the law. אמר רבא תדע, Amar Rava teida, you
should know דקטלי דיקלי, d'katlei diklei, they chop down palm trees, meaning
they say people owe them taxes, they go into their property, they
cut down their palm trees, וגשרי גישרי, v'gashri gishrei, and they make
bridges out of it. ועברינן עלייהו, V'avrinan aleihu, and we use the
bridges. So the fact is if we treated that when the government
seized property, if we treated it as גזל, gezel. right? So you
know, so then why would we be able to use these bridges?
It's made out of stolen wood. So it proves, again, not that
when they say something you have to listen to them, it proves
that they have right to seize property, to impose monetary obligations and
so on. So they're basically saying, like if that's the only bridge
and that's the only way to get out of the town, they
wouldn't be allowed to get out of the town? If it's גזל
gezel. you wouldn't. Anyway, it doesn't matter. The point is that we
have no compunctions making use of, you know, the benefits and the
property whatever that the government takes in taxes from other people. So
clearly we do not consider it all to be גזל. gezel All
right. אמר ליה אביי Amar lei Abaye but again, it's not saying
that we have to actually like follow the laws. That's not the
point that's being made here. אמר ליה אביי ודילמא משום דיאוש למינהו
מרייהו. Amar lei Abaye v'dilma mishum d'yaush laminahu mareihu. No, maybe that's
because, maybe it's גזל, but maybe the owners were מתיאש, mityaiesh, and
I don't know, what is it? Is it יאוש ושינוי השם yeush
v'shinui hashem or something? Anyway, but maybe it works within the normal
laws of גזל. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said, אי לאו
דינא דמלכותא דינא, i lav dina d'malchuta dina, no, if it weren't
really דינא דמלכותא dina d'malchuta. דינא, היכי מיאש? heichi miyash? So then
it wouldn't be good יאוש. yeush? Now what do you mean it
wouldn't be good יאוש? yeush? What sort of be good יאוש? yeush.
Because like I don't care whether technically it's the law or not,
I don't think I'm ever going to be able to get it
back from the government. No, here's why it wouldn't really be good
יאוש. yeush. והא לא קא veha lo ka I'm sorry, no, it
ends there. It would not be good יאוש. yeush? Okay, so it's
not really, it's really a strange claim because what do you mean
it wouldn't be good יאוש? yeush? Whether or not הלכה halacha recognizes
it, then, you know, I'm never hoping to get it back, they
took it, they're stronger than I am. So if you look at
רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says היכי מיאש, heichi miyash, it's like רש״י
Rashi right before the lines get wide in the גמרא. Gemara, רש״י
Rashi says כלומר מי הוי יאוש, klomar mi havei yeush, היאוש כדי
הוי. hayeush k'dei havei. It says who cares that it's יאוש? yeush
It's not, יאוש yeush isn't enough. You need יאוש ושינוי רשות, yeush
v'shinui reshus, okay? דאין כאן שינוי רשות d'ein kan shinui reshus דברשותא
דרבים הינהו, d'birshusa d'rabbim hinhu, דשינוי מעשה נמי ליכא d'shinui ma'aseh nami
leika דאכתי גופא דדקלא מיקרי. d'achti gufa d'dikla mikrei. So רש״י Rashi
says the point is יאוש is not enough to explain not that
the owners aren't מתיאש. mityaiesh. Of course they're מתיאש. mityaiesh. They never
hope they're going to get their palm trees back from the government.
But it would not be enough to explain how we could use
it without hesitation. So the fact that we use what the government
takes without any compunctions and hesitations proves that we're not dealing with
גזל. Proves that they have a right to take it. If they
say the person owes it, they have a right to take it.
But now the גמרא Gemara goes on. The גמרא Gemara says, one
minute. והא, veha, says the גמרא, Gemara לא קא עבדי כדאמרי מלכא.
lo ka'avdi k'da'amrei malka. The tax collectors aren't following their what the
king says. They're, well we'll see what they're doing, and therefore, like
we said before, when they act outside of the parameters of the
government, it should be it should not be דין. din. Why are
they not doing what the king says? מלכא אמר זילו וקטולו מכל
באגי. Malka amar zilu v'ktulu mikol bagei. The king says go take
five percent of palm trees from every copse, is that what it's
called a copse? You know, from every swath, every person has to
contribute five percent. And they are lazy. So what they do is,
they find one patch of palm trees and they cut down it
all, rather than distributing it among the hundred people in the village.
ואינהו אזלו וקטלו מחד באגא. v'inhu azlu v'ktalu mihad baga. They cut
it all down from one swamp, from one patch of land. Okay,
so they're not following. The king says to take it equally. גמרא
Gemara says no. שלוחא דמלכא כמלכא Shlucha d'malka k'malka ולא טרח. v'lo
tarach. No, when a king gives over this agency, this assignment, this
job, they have discretion and they're operating with the king's permission. Okay,
now so meaning before we said you can go outside, like you
can ask more money than you're entitled to, but this is a
discretionary matter. Now why is it discretionary? You know, it's not fair,
one person is suffering the whole tax burden. So the גמרא Gemara
says no. ואינהו אפסידו אנפשייהו v'inhu afsidu anafshaihu because the villagers, it's
their fault. They have a way of dealing with this situation. What's
their way of dealing with this situation? דאיבעי להו דאיפתו מכולי באגי
ומשקלו דמי. d'iba'ei lehu d'iptu mikulei bagei umishklu dmei. What they should
do is is that they should go ahead and get the village
together and operate that everybody contributes, right, and get everybody to pay
equally and give that money to the king's officer, and if they're
not and they know what the king's officer can do and what
his discretion is and if he's going to come and take, he's
working within his discretion. Maybe then they have a right to go
and the guy who had all of his palm trees taken to
go to the rest of the villagers and say I want to
be compensated, you got to share in the burden or whatever, but
the point is all of this is within acceptable parameters. And therefore
it's within דינא דמלכותא. dina d’malchuta. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so now
that we're dealing with like some what are some of those parameters
we're going to spell it out. אמר רבא מאן דמשתכח בבי דרי,
Amar Rava man d'mishtakach b'bei darei, if the guy is found in
the threshing floor and the the king the tax collector comes in,
okay, and he's got there now the grain of ten people in
that threshing floor. He happens to be there when the tax collector
comes in and the tax collector just takes from him, okay, because
he's the one there, but he takes the amount appropriate for the
full amount of grain in the whole threshing floor. He's basically making
him pay for other people's debts. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says,
he says, פרע מנתא דמלכא. para manta d'malka. He yes, he pays
the tax and the way רש״י Rashi says it is, you know,
similar to what we said before, and then that's acceptable, that's within
the tax collector's discretion, and then the other people who had the
grain they have to reimburse him. I mean that's not being said
in the גמרא Gemara but that's like what is being assumed. Okay,
but that is the guy is still operating, the tax collector within
the discretion he has, let everybody else work out, you know, sharing
in the burden. והני מילי שותפא, V'hani milei shutfa, that's only if
they are like partners in the grain and he winds up though
paying for more than his share. אבל אריסא, Aval arisa, somebody was
just a sharecropper, אריסותא הוא דקא מפיק, arisusa hu d'ka mafik, then
he is just taking out his percentage. he doesn’t really owe the
taxes and therefore the tax collector is not operating within his discretion
to make the sharecropper pay the taxes. Okay and then it would
be more of a גזל concern and so on. Alright, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. ואמר רבא בר מתנא בר מתנא מיעבד. V’amar
Rava bar Matna bar Matna mi’avad. Now I actually, okay, so this
is a similar point, okay, this is that basically I can go
ahead and wait a minute... right I can go ahead, I'm the
king's tax collector, I can go ahead for David and say, David
you know I'm really having a hard time getting Dov to pay
me his taxes, but I know that you can exert pressure, you're
his friend or whatever, so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to seize your car until Dov can pay up his taxes.
Dov doesn't have a nice car to seize, you've got this nice
little Jaguar which I have my eye on. I'm going to seize
your Jaguar until Dov pays his taxes. Okay and I actually am
operating within my discretion to do it, okay because that actually you
know that's considered within the דינא דמלכותא. dina d’malchuta, In the end
you know Dov has to pay, it's not like you're going to
have to pay, he's going to have to pay, but I can
do this as a way of getting him to pay. והני מילי
דובלא דבר לארעא דכראגא, V’hanei milei dubla d’var l’ara d’charga, that’s only
like a land tax and a head tax דהאי שתא d’hai shata
of this year. אבל שתא דחליף Aval shata d’chalif if it’s last
year’s taxes which I’ve already given the money to the king that
I owe for last year’s taxes and now I’m collecting back taxes,
in that case when I’m collecting back taxes I have less discretion.
הואיל ופייס מלכא Ho’il u’fayeis malka since the king was appeased, meaning
whatever the king collected for last year, he basically, even if it
wasn't the full amount, he's you know he made his peace with
it, that's what we were able to collect. So even though I
have a right to collect back taxes, since it's not as much
of you know any more of the moment, right then that my
discretion is a little bit less. In that case כיוון דפייס מלכא
חליף keivan d’fayeis malka chalif like okay last year's last year. So
presumably it means I still can collect taxes, but I don't have
as much discretion to do this type of pressure. ואמר רבא V’amar
Rava now Rava also said, הני דדיירי דארי בתוך התחום, hanei d’dayri
dari b’toch ha’tchum, people that graze animals, this really seems to be
shifting the conversation to somewhere else. People that are grazing animals, if
they do it within the תחום, tchum, like within the you know
the region right outside the city, they don't go far from the
city, אסור ליקח מהם assur l’kach meihem you can’t buy animals from
them. מאי טעמא משום דמערבי חיותא דמתא בהדייהו Mai ta’ama mishum d’m’arvi
chiyuta d’mata bahadeihu since they stay so close to the city, the
village, the other animals of the village get mixed up with theirs.
So this is really going back to the concern of the משנה.
Mishna. We're no longer דינא דמלכותא, dina d’malchuta we're no longer גזל
גוי. It's like you somebody has something the same way the tax
collector had money and some of the money in the pouch was
stolen or all the money in the pouch was stolen, or whatever,
this shepherd has sheep and some of the sheep aren't his, so
therefore you have to avoid buying sheep from him because there might
be stolen sheep among them. חוץ לתחום Chutz l’tchum however if they
only graze their sheep outside of the city, like except long far
from the city, מותר ליקח מהם mutar l’kach meihem then you can,
then you don't have to be concerned that there are other sheep
mixed up. אמר רבינא Amar Ravina אם היו בעלים מרדפים אחריהן im
hayu ba’alim m’radfim achareihen but if the owners were running after the
shepherd and say, wait wait you got my sheep mixed up in
there, in that case אפילו חוץ לתחום אסור afilu chutz l’tchum assur
even presumably he means even if they can't prove it, but nevertheless
if that seems if the circumstances are indicating that then you can't
buy from them even outside. מכריז רבא Machriz Rava Rava announced ואיתימא
רב הונא v’iteima Rav Huna דסלקין לעילא ודנחתין לתתא, d’salkin l’eila u’d’nachtin
l’tata, those that go above and come down, sounds like Jacob's ladder,
those that go to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and come from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael to here, the following הלכה halacha he announced it.
האי בר ישראל דידע סהדותא לכותי, Hai bar Yisrael d’yada sahaduta l’Kuti,
now we're shifting back to a type of דינא דמלכותא discussion or
a Jew and a non-Jew who are coming to court, but it
also raises other issues about participating in a non-Jewish court system. Okay
so again this actually is good, right, if a Jew has knows
testimony to help support a non-Jew, okay, and presumably who has a
case against a Jew, okay but you actually know that the non-Jew
is right, you saw the Jew borrow money and so on, right,
should you go and testify or not. And so the question- so
he says ולא תבעו מיניה, v’lo tva’u minei, there's a question whether
those three words are in the גמרא, okay, and you have not
been summoned to court then you shouldn't go. Some say even if
you have been summoned you shouldn't go, there's a question if those
three words are there. But reading it with those words, you know
testimony for a non- to support a non-Jew, you have not been
summoned to court ואזיל ואסהיד ליה בדיני דגויים על ישראל חבריה v’azil
v’ashid lei b’dinei d’goyim al Yisrael chavrei and you go and you
testify in a non-Jewish court supporting a non-Jew in his case against
a Jew, in that case משמתינן ליה m’shamtinan lei we put you
in חרם, cherem, you should not be doing that. Okay now מאי
טעמא mai ta’ama what's the reason? What if it was you're saying
it's a- you were- yeah the non-Jew was right, okay, but nevertheless
don't go to their court supporting them. Now why is that? Is
it because of a general issue, well we're going to see, you
could raise generally you're not supposed to participate. non-Jewish courts at all,
even take your fellow Jew to a non-Jewish court, right? There's that
whole discourse, you know, there's that whole literature about that. It could
just be because you know you're always supposed to try to help
the Jew win even if it's not really deserved, like we sort
of discussed before. Okay? But it's one thing to tell me I
don't have to pay, it's another thing to say if I try
to make to to have justice served like even though may then
somehow I did something wrong, like to you know so let's see
what the גמרא says. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Let me just say
you said it's a questionable phrase whether he was asked or not
asked. Right. So if he's asked, if he's asked then there's more
of an argument that he can go regardless because then he'll get
in trouble if he doesn't. And they'll excommunicate if he wasn't? Yeah.
If you don't have that phrase, then the answer would be yes.
But we have the phrase. It was only when he wasn't summoned.
מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? I mean at the end
of the day you know this testimony or whatever. דאינהו מפיק ממונא
אפומא דחד De'inhu mafik mamona apuma dechad because even you'll be a
solitary witness, you saw the Jew borrow money, and בדיני ישראל nobody
would have paid money based on one witness, and they will accept
one witness and they'll make him pay. Now the bottom line is,
but he owes the money! Meaning it might be true that in
terms of procedure there are not two witnesses, but I genuinely know
that the Jew borrowed the money. But somehow since he can win
either because either because he can win in a Jewish court I
shouldn't be helping him win in a different legal system even though
objectively speaking he owes the money. It's sort of like the discussion
before about אפקסתא דאבשא, afkasta de'avsha, or maybe it's just more the
issue of I shouldn't be participating in a legal system that doesn't
follow like the תורה Torah's הלכה. Halacha. Okay, but it still feels
very strange because the reality is he owes the money. Anyway, let's
just finish this. ולא אמרן אלא חד. Velo amran ela chad. That's
only if you're one witness. אבל בתרי לא, Aval bitrei lo, if
you're two witnesses and you were summoned, since the non-Jew would win
in the Jewish court, you can also go and testify in the
non-Jewish court. והכא נמי לא אמרן אלא בדיני דמגיסתא Vecha nami lo
amran ela bedinei de'megista which Rashi says means like a village you
know court which does based on one witness. אבל בדבר Aval be'davar
which Rashi says means like a larger governmental court, אינהו נמי חד
אמומתא שדו ליה. inhu nami chad amamusa shadlei. They also follow the
type of Jewish law procedures and one witness they only impose an
oath, they don't actually extract money. So therefore it is actually acceptable
in that case, you know, because it's following the same thing as
it would in דיני ישראל. dinei Yisrael. Again, there's two questions. One
is helping you know like like are you trying to prevent the
help the Jew or help the non-Jew take money that they deserve
or don't deserve or whatever, and the other is the question about
is there a general problem of participating in a non-Jewish legal system.
And let's just give me one more minute I just want to
read to the משנה Mishnah we're so far behind just to take
literally take just one more minute. איבעיא לן. Iba'ya lan. So they
I'm sorry. So אמר רב אשי. amar Rav Ashi. Rav Ashi said,
כי הוינא בי רב כהנא ki havina bei Rav Kahana when I
was at Rav Kahana, איבעיא לן, iba'ya lan, we have the following
question. אדם חשוב, Adam chashuv, let's say you're one witness but you're
a very חשוב chashuv person, you know, somebody who they put a
lot who has a lot of weight. דסמכי עליה כבתרי Desamchi alei
kebitrei and people trust you like two people, certainly the non-Jewish court.
מפיק ממונא אפומא Mafik mamona apumei ולא איבעי ליה לאסהודי velo iba'i
lei le'asudi do we say because of that, you know, you should
not testify because they will use your single testimony and extract money
even though you're only one witness and you shouldn't participate in a
system that's going to extract money based on one witness? או דלמא,
Odilma, or do we say כיון דאדם חשוב הוא keivan de'adam chashuv
hu since you're such a חשוב chashuv person, לא מצי משתמיט להו,
lo matu mishtamit lehu, you're going to get in a lot of
trouble if you avoid going to court like a normal person who
avoids, you know, whatever, they don't care so much or they don't
pay so much attention. But you, they've got their eye on you!
So for your own self-protection you have to go and and and
testify. תיקו. Teiku. We don't know. אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi.
האי בר ישראל דזבין ליה ארעא לעכו"ם Hai bar Yisrael dezavin lei
ara le'aku'm אמצרא דבר ישראל חבריה, amitzra debar Yisrael chavrei, if a
Jew sells a plot of land to a non-Jew who is who
and it's the plot of land borders on another Jew's land. Right,
דדינא דבר מצרא. de'dina de'bar mitzra. So I've got land, you David
this land abuts your land and you would love to buy it
because then you could exceed your acreage, right, having a big plot
all in one place is great for you. And rather than giving
you right of first refusal, I offer it to the non-Jew. Right.
משמתינן ליה. Meshamtinan lei. So the so the seller's put in חרם.
cherem. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why? אינימא משום דינא דבר מצרא Ineima
mishum dina de'bar mitzra for the of the neighboring of the neighbor's
field that you're supposed to give the guy right of first refusal.
ואמר מר, Ve'amar Mar, but we say זבין מגויה וזבין לגויה לית
בה משום דינא דבר מצרא. zavin migu'y vezavin legu'y leit bei mishum
dina de'bar mitzra. That doesn't apply when you're selling when you're buying
to and from a non-Jew, which is strange, why shouldn't it? Okay,
but anyway, אלא דאמרינן ליה, ela de'amrinan lei, no rather the reason
is that forget the idea first refusal, because I have a non-Jew
now as your neighbor, you can say to me, ארבעית אריא אמצראי,
arveiti aryeh amitzrei, you're putting a lion right by my borders. Again,
this reflects the idea that they thought the non-Jews were violent and
גזלנים gazlanim and so on. So he's going to go ahead and
he's going to encroach on my land, he's going to steal my
crops, that's why. So the גמרא says, משמתינן ליה meshamtinan leh because
it's about the concern that he might injure you, or you know
or steal from you, the the seller is put in חרם cherem
עד דקבליה כל אונסא דאתי מחמתיה ad dekableh kol onsa de'ati machmateh
until he accepts liability for any any loss. If I accept financial
liability for the fact that he's your neighbor, then it's okay. And
the laws of דינא דבר מצרא dina debar metzra though would not
apply, that's a whole separate בבא בתרא Bava Batra discussion. Okay, we
will end here, still so we now are